<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of Christianity</title>
            <author>Blount, Walter Kirkham, Sir, d. 1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11751592</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11751592</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 168:12, 811:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of Christianity</title>
                  <author>Blount, Walter Kirkham, Sir, d. 1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the King" signed: Walter Kirkham Blount.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [10].</note>
                  <note>This work appears on reels 168 and 811.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library and Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>Item incorrectly called B5352 in Wing reel guide.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPIRIT OF Chriſtianity.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of two flying storks or cranes fighting for a snake or worm; in the background a town in the countryside; the whole framed by a snake with its tail in its mouth (worm ouroboros), forming a circle (similar to the printer's device of Sébastien Nivelle, 1523/5-1603 and Sébastien Cramoisy, 1585-1669)</figDesc>
               <byline>S.G.</byline>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, for his Houſhold and Chappel. 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S welcom as the Argument of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe always is to Your Majeſty, and as happy as the Author has been to pleaſe You with his managing it, I do not Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it yet without a great deal of diffidence. 'Tis now I fear too courſly Dreſt to
<pb facs="tcp:48587:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thruſt it into the <hi>Preſence.</hi> I might peradventure with as good a Grace make Your Majeſty a Preſent of wither'd Flowers, or Fruit blown down and bruis'd with the Fall. But Scriblers are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with the Spirit of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and make bold with the Names of Princes at every turn and to every Trifle: with which their Goodneſs has had ſo long patience, that Men offend now by Preſcription. And I perhaps moſt of all, who ſin knowingly; and with a
<pb facs="tcp:48587:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtrong check from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion I have, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of officious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinence is not the lighteſt of the many Burdens which ſit ſo heavy on Greatneſs. But 'tis mine and all Your Subjects comfort, that Your Majeſty can pardon greater Faults: And that he is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure enough from being ill receiv'd, who entertains You with <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> though in never ſo plain a Faſhion. This comfort has flatter'd me into the boldneſs of
<pb facs="tcp:48587:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>gratifying my Ambition, by owning to all the World how much I glory in the happineſs of being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſty's Moſt humble, moſt faithful and moſt dutiful Subject</hi> Walter Kirkham Blount.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:4"/>
            <head>TABLE OF CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> IN what conſiſts the true Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Nature and Qualities of this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in which conſiſts the Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and the <hi>Idea</hi> of a Chriſtian. <hi>Pag. 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the true practice of Charity, according to the Spirit of Chriſtianity. <hi>Pag. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> In what Order Chriſtian Charity ought to be practiſed. <hi>Pag. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the ſeveral Illuſions to which the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Charity is ſubject. <hi>Pag. 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Means to acquire Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Pag. 101.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:48587:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Three powerful Motives to excite a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to acquire the Vertue of Charity. <hi>Pag. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Concluſion of this Diſcourſe by way of Exhortation, to move Chriſtians to Charity. <hi>Pag. 124.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 11. <hi>line</hi> 18. <hi>read</hi> blood ſhed. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> coveted to. <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> one ſoul. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> too much. <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> as we ought. <hi>p.</hi> 87. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> Command. <hi>p.</hi> 93. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> is it ſelf. <hi>p.</hi> 94. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; <hi>p.</hi> 96. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> they advance. <hi>p.</hi> 97 <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> reflect on: <hi>p.</hi> 100. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> open'd to. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> Is it as much. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>r.</hi> the mean? <hi>p.</hi> 120. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>r.</hi> reign ſo. <hi>p.</hi> 118. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> life the.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48587:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SPIRIT OF CHRISTIANITY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> In what conſiſts the true Spirit of Chriſtianity.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> a Name ſanctified by the Lives of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who were the firſt Faithful, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by the bloud of ſo many Martyrs, a Name ſo divine, that it filled the World heretofore with the fame of its glory, is at preſent but as a glimmering light juſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and as a faint ſhadow of what it was in its infancy. 'Tis true, that there
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48587:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>never was, perhaps, ſo much talk of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity as in theſe latter Times; for every place now rings with the Duties of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſo holy; Nothing is in our mouth, but the firſt Ages, and purity of the Spirit of the Primitive Church: but after all, we may ſay very juſtly, there were never ſo few true Chriſtians as now adays. The looſneſs, the exceſs, the corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in theſe Times, have ſo disfigured in our hearts the features of this moſt ſacred Character, that there ſcarce remains the leaſt ſign of it. Fain would we enjoy the honor belonging to this Name, without knowing the price of it; We attribute to our ſelves this glorious quality, without concern for what's to be done to deſerve it; And we vainly boaſt our ſelves to be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as knowing by what ſpirit we ought to be Chriſtians. Thus we loſe the advantage of ſo elevated a dignity, through the little care we take to learn its obligations. 'Tis then to be wiſht, that to remedy this evil, a Chriſtian be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the nobleneſs of his Condition, and holineſs of its Duties, by making him comprehend what the Spirit of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is. It is a Deſign of ſuch importance, that I ſhould have been far enough from undertaking it of my ſelf, had not God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48587:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>inſpired me to do it, as much for my own inſtruction, as the edification of ſuch as ſhall take the pains to read this ſmall Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Although one cannot be a Chriſtian but by Faith: yet one cannot live and act like a Chriſtian but by Charity; ſince the Spirit of Chriſtianity conſiſts only in Charity. To underſtand this Truth, we need only conſider the Motives of the Incarnation and Paſſion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which are the two fundamental Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion. In effect, as we are only Chriſtians by the heavenly alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Son of God with our Nature, and by the ineſtimable price of his Bloud; we degenerate from that Spirit wherein we were conceived, if we partake not in the holy motions of that fervent Charity, which was the principle of theſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For the Saviour of the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Man meerly to ſave Man. In his Incarnation he took on himſelf our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, only to free us from them. He em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced poverty in his birth, only to enrich us; He ſuffered death in his Paſſion, only to give us life; And what is more to be admired, Man was worthy of nothing but his hate, when God gave him ſuch ſignal teſtimonies of his love.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48587:8"/>
               <p>Before this ineffable Myſtery, we had ſome Idea of the Greatneſs, Power, and Majeſty of God; but we had, ſays S. <hi>Paul,</hi> no manner of knowledge of his Mercy and Goodneſs. The exceſs of this love has appeared in the ſequel, ſo much above the wit of Man, that all human reaſon, as <hi>Salvian</hi> aſſures us, has not hitherto been well able to juſtifie the diſproportion of the price of the death of an innocent Son, which God gave, to redeem guilty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. 'Tis true, that from the firſt ſtep the Son of God made, by his Incarnation, towards the Salvation of Mankind, the whole courſe of his life appears very op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to ours. He would be born in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and diſtreſs, who might have been born in greatneſs and plenty; to teach us, that he ſeeks us, not our wealth and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and that he requires nothing of us, but our ſelves: He concerns himſelf with nothing elſe. He is ſo far from avoiding our ignominy, that he made himſelf like us, only to take it upon him; and diveſts himſelf of his Greatneſs, to cloath himſelf with our meanneſs.</p>
               <p>But to give us yet greater teſtimonies of his love, he transforms himſelf into all ſhapes that tenderneſs can inſpire, to do us good. Now he is a ſollicitous Shepherd,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48587:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>running after the ſtrayed Sheep, to bring him back to the Flock. Then he is a Father, compaſſionate of the miſery to which debauchery had brought his Son, whom he reclaims, by managing the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the young Man, with all the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the bowels of a Father. A Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is wounded by Thieves on the Road to <hi>Jericho,</hi> and he becomes a Phyſician to his Wounds. A <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and he charitably ſets himſelf to inſtruct her, thereby to gain her: and that thirſt he would quench, by drinking the Water he demanded from her, is only the figure of a greater thirſt and zeal which he had for her ſalvation. He humbles himſelf to appear unto <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> even like a Gardener; and to comfort her, he converſes familiarly with her in ſo mean an outſide. To be ſhort, he becomes a Traveller with the Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> to free them from that doubt and trouble into which their diſtruſt had thrown them.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel is full of a thouſand other teſtimonies of his bounty towards us. When we flie from him, he follows us; He calls us, when we forget him: He preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly urges us, when we will not hear him. When we ſlight him, he complains
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48587:9"/>kindly of us: And when we return to him, after having offended him, he ſeems ſo ſenſible, that he takes more pleaſure to make his own joy, and that of his whole coeleſtial Court break out at the repentance of one ſinner, then at the fidelity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance of a great number of Juſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his glory appears more in pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then puniſhing. St. <hi>John</hi> thunders forth nothing but threats and terrors to his Hearers, becauſe he ſpeaks in the ſpirit of <hi>Elias: Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſays nothing but what is ſweet and mild; becauſe he ſpeaks accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Maximes, and in his own Spirit, which is that of the law of Grace.</p>
               <p>But never did the love of God towards Man appear more, then at his Paſſion. For that very night, wherein Man conſpired his death, this God of goodneſs thought of nothing but to leave him marks of his mercy and tenderneſs: And at the ſame time that one of his Diſciples, by the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Treaſons, betrayed him to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be put to death, he gave his moſt ſacred Body for food for their Souls. He died at laſt loaded with reproach and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny, after having been dragged from Tribunal to Tribunal, forſaken by his own Diſciples, and abandoned by all the World. He died a publick and infamous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48587:9"/>Death, nailed to a Croſs; amidſt the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of thoſe that put him to death: But he died with a ſilence, a ſweetneſs, a tranquility, a patience, a peace, and quiet, which aſtoniſht his very Executioners. They reproacht him when he was dying, that he could ſave others, but not himſelf. Nor was this reproach without reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thought no longer of himſelf, but only of men. And amidſt the horrors of ſo cruel a Death, plunged in a ſea of grief and bitterneſs, he never open'd his dying eyes, nor turn'd them towards heaven, but to implore the mercy of his Father, even for thoſe that put him to death, ſaying, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> He ſhed his Bloud, he died for the ſalvation of the Executioners that crucified him. What exceſs of love! How incomprehenſible to our capacity! S. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> had reaſon to ſay, That the greateſt teſtimony <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave of his Divinity, was the extending his love even to all thoſe who killed him: for, nothing leſs then God could love at a rate, ſo much above the reach of Man.</p>
               <p>But though the Expreſſions of that love which the Son of God had for Man, are very obſervable in divers places of the Old Teſtament, under the Figures of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48587:10"/>Patriarchs and Prophets: yet are they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where more ſtrong and tender, then in the New Teſtament, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſpeaks of it, as of one of the moſt eſſential Points of his Doctrine. So as the whole Morality of the Goſpel turns on this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, That the true Spirit of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is, to have charity for on's Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Every thing conſpires to ſettle there this important Maxime, which is the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Point of our Religion. For, though the Evangeliſts wrote nothing by agreement, and that the Goſpel ſeems to have been publiſht, rather upon occaſion, then by deſign: yet ſince 'tis the Doctrine of their Maſter they write, we find therein ſo great a conformity of Sentiments on this Principle of Chriſtian Charity, that it ſufficiently appears by their manner of declaring it, there is nothing more eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Chriſtianity, then the love of our Neighbour. <hi>The whole law,</hi> ſays St. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, <hi>is comprehended in this precept. 'Tis the moſt important of all,</hi> ſays St. Mark. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> carries it to a higher pitch of perfection, in St. <hi>Luke;</hi> where he obliges the faithful, repreſented by his Apoſtles, <hi>To love their enemies, to do good for evil, and to pray for their calumniators.</hi> Laſt of all, St. <hi>John,</hi> who knew moſt of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48587:10"/>Maſters ſecrets, and penetrated deepeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his thoughts, places the eſſential mark of a Chriſtian, in the love of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>By this all men ſhall know,</hi> ſays our Saviour by the mouth of this Apoſtle, <hi>that you are my diſciples, if you love one another.</hi> This is the commandment of the law of Grace, whereunto is reduced all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the New Teſtament; And the Saviour of the World recommended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo earneſtly to his Diſciples, in the laſt moments of his life, as Concord and Union: Becauſe this Union was to be the foundation of the Religion he eſtabliſht.</p>
               <p>The Evangeliſts do not only ſpeak all according to this Principle; but 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent the ſame Spirit makes them ſpeak. They treat their friends and enemies both alike in their Hiſtory. A God murthered by men, and an innocent man oppreſſed by calumny, might have afforded their zeal ſome reaſon for exaggeration: yet they allow themſelves nothing, which has any ſhew of emotion or violence. They relate the treaſon of <hi>Judas,</hi> the cruelty of the Executioners, the injuſtice and violence of the Magiſtrates, without any touch of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs againſt their perſons. They ſpeak in a way, apt to make one believe, they had no concern in what they ſay. A ſpirit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48587:11"/>ſo unintereſted is without example, and whereof the common ſort of men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable. 'Tis only Chriſtianity, that is to ſay, a Diſcipline wholly coeleſtial, which can inſpire ſo much moderation.</p>
               <p>We ſee the firſt fruits of this Spirit in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> which is the Hiſtory of the eſtabliſhment of Chriſtianity. For, as the Hiſtorian relates, the Chriſtians did then live in ſuch a Union, as if they had all one and the ſame heart, and one and the ſame ſoul The propriety of Goods, which ordinarily cauſes diſſentions amongſt men, was no obſtacle to this Union; for all their Goods were in common: They brought, and laid at the feet of the Apoſtles, their Revenues, Rents, Bonds, Contracts, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and all the Wealth which each one poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed. This diſengagement from all things, united them more firmly together: They had but one ſpirit, becauſe they had but one intereſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt flames of this love broke out at the death of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> who had the glory to lay his life firſt down for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Stones flew about him from all parts; The Plains eccho'd with the cries of thoſe that encourag'd one another to kill this holy Levite; His face was batter'd with blows, his ribs broken, his breaſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48587:11"/>beaten through, his breath e'en quite gone, and yet he employed the little ſtrength he had left, in begging Gods pardon for thoſe that had treated him ſo cruelly: <hi>Lord,</hi> ſays he as he was dying, <hi>lay not this ſin to their charge.</hi> Thus to forget himſelf, and employ his laſt words and ſighs, in ſolliciting God in behalf of a Crime committed upon himſelf, was to tread the very ſteps of his Maſter, and to be wholly poſſeſt with his ſpirit; and to have no thoughts but theſe of tenderneſs, in the very pangs of ſo cruel and bitter a death, was to die generouſly like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. How pure and holy is the Spirit of Chriſtianity, which inſpired ſo much mercy; and of how great inſtruction to Chriſtians, the ſacrifice of this firſt bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for the love of <hi>Jeſus!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee in the progreſs of the ſame Hiſtory, the Apoſtles animated by this Spirit, to run through the whole World, to preach and teach the Goſpel to all Nations: And that neither the moſt ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sands of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> nor the Deſarts of <hi>Africa,</hi> nor the Froſts of <hi>Scythia,</hi> nor the remoteſt parts of <hi>India,</hi> nor Seas, nor Tempeſts, nor Rocks, nor Treaſons, nor Calumnies, nor contradiction of People, nor oppoſition of Laws, nor Magiſtrates,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48587:12"/>nor Governors of Provinces, nor all the Power of the World, nor Chains, nor Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor Gibbets, nor even the moſt cruel Deaths, were able to withſtand their zeal, nor ſhake the conſtancy of their hearts. Dangers encourage them, difficulties ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate them, and their own weakneſſes ſtrengthen them: Becauſe the charity by which they are poſſeſt, renders their own lives inconſiderable, when the ſalvation of their Neighbour is in queſtion. The truth is, they did miracles, which ſtruck people with admiration. They commanded the Winds, and Tempeſts, Seaſons obeyed them, and even Nature her ſelf in ſome ſort became their Slave: But after all, the greateſt of their Miracles, was their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. 'Twas alſo this Charity, which made them with pleaſure ſacrifice their honor and life, to carry the light of the Goſpel to the moſt remote Nations of the Earth, and draw them out of the profound blindneſs, wherein they were. This holy Doctrine flew through the World, whilſt thoſe that preacht it, were themſelves in Chains and Priſons: And nothing perſwaded ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the embracing of the Goſpel, as the Charity of thoſe that publiſht it. Things in themſelves incredible were believed, though declared by ſuch as were perſecuted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48587:12"/>by the whole World; becauſe they that told them, did firſt practiſe themſelves what they taught others; Nor was it neceſſary they ſhould Preach at all, ſays St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> becauſe their life was a continual Sermon. 'Tis true, that the Infidels were ſcandalized at their Perſecutions, their Fetters, their Impriſonments, and their Sufferings: But the very Union, in which they lived, was ſo powerful, that they, who moſt reviled their Sufferings, ſubmitted to the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe inflamed with the ſame zeal, could not behold the reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Jews, a People heretofore ſo che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht by God, without offering up himſelf in quality of a Victim, and wiſhing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf anathematized for his Brethren. He, who had ſo highly proteſted, that neither Heaven, nor Hell, nor any thing created, ſhould be able to ſeparate him from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> now begs to be ſeparated from him, for the ſalvation of his People. St. <hi>John,</hi> that beloved Diſciple of our Lord, had nothing ſo deeply engraven in his heart, as this love for his Neighbour. This was the only practice of vertue he preacht to his Diſciples, as an abridgment of the whole Law of Grace, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> aſſures us. <hi>Love one another,</hi> ſays he, <hi>my
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48587:13"/>dear children, 'tis the only thing I have to tell you, becauſe 'tis the only thing needful to be done.</hi> He of all others ſpeaks moſt clearly of this Doctrine, becauſe he had the advantage of others, to ſound the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of his Maſter, by reaſon of the confidence <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was pleaſed to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor him with above his other Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Throughout the whole courſe of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtory there are found ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent tracts of this Spirit, that it ſeems as if the Chriſtians endeavoured only by Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to diſtinguiſh themſelves from Pagans. In their lives there appeared ſuch viſible marks of that new fire, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to bring into the World, that Chriſtians were known by their Union: And this fire, wherewith their hearts were full, flam'd with ſuch a light, that it could not be darkned with Calumny, nor extinguiſht by Perſecution. It was likewiſe that voice of Love and Charity, which in preaching of the Goſpel, was underſtood by the fierceſt and moſt barbarous Nations, and afterwards did chiefly contribute to the eſtabliſhment of Faith. The Heathens ſaid, ſpeaking of the Faithful, They are obliging, charitable, always doing good; therefore they are Chriſtians: for their Belief, their Morality, and their Goſpel, is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48587:13"/>to love their Neighbour, and do good to every one. They believed this new Religion true, becauſe it commanded one Man to love another, which is the moſt reaſonable and juſt Command of all others. They became Chriſtians, perceiving in how perfect an Union the Chriſtians lived. Their meekneſs, goodneſs, affability, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and inclination to oblige every one, more powerfully moved the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to embrace the Doctrine which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſo well-doing a Vertue, then all they did. And the Faith advanced the faſter, by the good opinion people had conceived of his holineſs, who was author of ſo pure a Law: according to the Prayer himſelf had made to his Father, ſpeaking of the Faithful; <hi>to the end,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they may be united in us, and that the world toucht with this Union, may believe that it is you, my Father, who has ſent me.</hi> The Union wherein Chriſtians ought to live, is the chief Reaſon Chriſt uſes to authorize his Miſſion, and excite peoples Faith.</p>
               <p>In effect, this Union was ſo great in the firſt Ages, that St. <hi>Clement,</hi> a Diſciple of the Apoſtles, relates in one of his Epiſtles, that he had known divers Chriſtians in his time, who themſelves became Slaves, to free their Brethren out of Slavery; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48587:14"/>that he had ſeen others, who in a painful and laborious life, fed with the labours of their Hands thoſe that were in neceſſity. St. <hi>Juſtin,</hi> in the Apology he made for Religion, before the Emperors, to give thoſe Princes a great Idea of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, mixes throughout his Diſcourſe, the holy Ordinances which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gave the Chriſtians, to be charitable and well-doing; like their heavenly Father, who pours forth his Graces on the good and the bad. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in the Defence he made of our Religion in the Reign of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Severus,</hi> ſets forth moſt admirably well, the great Love and Union among Chriſtians, whereby they gain'd the eſteem of the People.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, that in the Reign of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> the Chriſtians did ſo often and liberally aſſiſt the impriſon'd Martyrs with their temporal Goods, that notorious Thieves counterfeited themſelves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and caſt themſelves into Priſon, that ſo they might partake of their ſuccour. A while after the Diſorders were ſo great in <hi>Africa,</hi> that a Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy them, was neceſſitated to forbid the Chriſtians to give theſe Alms, becauſe the Heathens themſelves did privately ſcoff at the Abuſes they committed therein.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48587:14"/>
               <p>But in proceſs of time, theſe Succours becoming more needful, through the great number of Martyrs, which increaſed with the Perſecution, the Alms were ſo regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that he took away the abuſe, without diminiſhing the abundance. The ſame S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> did by his Diſcourſes, ſo inflame the Charity of the <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that he gathered a vaſt ſum of Money, and therewith redeemed a great number of Chriſtian Captives, whom the Barbarians had carried into Slavery, when they entred the Confines of <hi>Numidia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Charity of the Chriſtians was more conſpicuous under the Emperor <hi>Gallienus,</hi> in the heat of that Civil War, which had almoſt ruin'd the City of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria:</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in his Hiſtory. The reciprocal aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that Chriſtians gave each other, was the more remarkable, becauſe the City was divided by two Factions, extreamly animated againſt each other. But this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Union was yet more eminent, in that diſmal Plague which followed the War, and deſtroyed that City, before moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing: They ſaw there, ſays <hi>Euſebius,</hi> the Chriſtians continually about the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and courageouſly expoſing themſelves to death, in exhorting them to offer up
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48587:15"/>their lives, in the ſubmiſſion of their heart: And after having received their laſt ſighs with pleaſure, they ſaw them waſh, kiſs, and bury their Bodies; Whilſt among the Pagans, Neighbour became jealous of Neighbour, Friend diſtruſted Friend; they that were neareſt related forſook each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in extremity. The Father left the Son, and the tendereſt Mothers cauſed the dead Bodies of their own Children to be caſt out of the Windows. In truth, the Chriſtians, that died in the Duties of ſuch fervent Charity, drew ſo great veneration from all people, that the Church of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> regiſtred them among the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Martyrs, whereof ſhe keeps a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Feſtival the laſt of <hi>February:</hi> And <hi>Euſebius</hi> mentions this Feaſt in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</p>
               <p>After all, there is nothing gives ſo lively a character of the Charity which then flouriſhed among Chriſtians, as what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to St. <hi>Pacomius.</hi> He being yet a Heathen, and having Liſted himſelf into the Troups of the Emperor <hi>Licinius,</hi> after a long and troubleſom Journey, arrived at laſt at <hi>Thebes.</hi> When all the Army came thither, the Chriſtians of that City brought them, with great joy and forwardneſs, all ſort of Refreſhments. This made him
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48587:15"/>enquire who thoſe charitable People were, <hi>that came thus thronging to relieve every one?</hi> They anſwer'd him, they were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who profeſſed 'twas their duty to do good to all the World. <hi>Metaphraſtus</hi> teſtifies, that <hi>Pacomius</hi> was ſo toucht with this ſpirit of well-doing, that he ardently courted to be one of thoſe ſo holy men, and he obtain'd his deſire: for ſhortly after this accident he obtain'd the Grace of God to become a Chriſtian. <hi>Evagrius</hi> makes an admirable deſcription of that Union wherein the Chriſtians lived at <hi>Thebes,</hi> where the Faith was ſtill in its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive fervour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, in the Life of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> that the humility of Chriſtianity had in ſuch manner annihilated in the ſoul of this Prince that pride, which Sovereignty inſpires, that when he became Maſter of the Empire, he no longer lookt on his Subjects as his Slaves, as the other Emperors had done, but he regarded them as his Brothers, and Fellow-ſervants of the ſame Maſter, and ſame God that he adored: And he made no other uſe of his Imperial Purple, then to fortifie his Authority, that he might make holy Ordinances for the eaſe of his People, and ſatisfie his great inclination to do good to ſuch as God had put under his Power.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48587:16"/>
               <p>The Forces of the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> being arrived at <hi>Antioch,</hi> to puniſh thoſe that had thrown down his Statues, the Hermits of the neighbouring Mountains and Deſarts round about, appear'd all at once iſſuing out of their ſolitary Dwellings and Caves, to implore clemency of the Emperours Officers, for ſuch as had offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Our Prince</hi> (cried out theſe holy Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits) <hi>is a Chriſtian, he will have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when he ſhall know our Complaints: and we ought not to ſuffer you to embrue your Hands in the bloud of our Brethren.</hi> Theſe holy Men, being repulſed by the Soldiers, addreſſed themſelves to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and obtain'd a delay of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They immediately put to Sea, and being arrived at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the Emperours feet, and offered their own Heads to ſave thoſe that were guilty. The whole Court admired the zeal of ſo fervent a Charity: And St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> aſſures us, that the Emperour having pardon'd their Offence, gain'd more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor by this act of his clemency, then he ever did by the luſtre of his Diadem. This great Saint could not ceaſe from praiſing the Law of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which had been ſo powerful to ſuppreſs the rage of ſo mighty a Prince, and to inſpire him with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48587:16"/>ſuch a mild temper, as few, even private, perſons are capable of.</p>
               <p>'Tis by the fervour of this Spirit too, that ſo many illuſtrious Ladies, who in the firſt Ages were the greateſt Ornaments of Chriſtianity, the <hi>Paula's,</hi> the <hi>Marcella's,</hi> the <hi>Albina's,</hi> the <hi>Melania's,</hi> the <hi>Flaccilla's,</hi> the <hi>Paulina's,</hi> did more honor to Religion, then by the nobleneſs of their Bloud and Birth, or the ſplendour of their Fortune. The ſtream of Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory is fill'd with Examples expreſſing this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, which then was found in Emperours and private perſons, in great and in little, in Men and Women; for in effect, this was the true Spirit of Chriſtianity, which in following Ages was found more or leſs fervent, according as Religion flouriſhed more or leſs. True it is, that this Charity never ſhew'd its ſelf in its full purity, but at its birth: and its brightneſs appear'd ſo much the greater at the beginning, as the Grace that encourag'd it was more ſtrong and more abundant: But although it ſeem, that Chriſtianity is become more weak and faint, as it runs on farther from its Source, through the courſe of ſo many Ages; yet from time to time ſome ſparks have ſhew'd themſelves of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine fire of Charity, which is the ſoul of it.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48587:17"/>
               <p>In theſe latter Times, as well as in the firſt Ages, <hi>Paulin's</hi> have been ſeen ſelling their own Liberties, to deliver their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from Servitude. There has been found more then once a <hi>John Calabite,</hi> and a <hi>John Almoner,</hi> who have diveſted themſelves of all things, to give all to the Poor. 'Tis read in St. <hi>Anſelm,</hi> that <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phegus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who liv'd in the beginning of the eleventh Age, being taken Priſoner by the Enemy, choſe rather to die, then conſent his Flock ſhould be overcharg'd for the ranſom of his life. I ſay nothing of St. <hi>Bernardin</hi> of <hi>Siena,</hi> nor of St. <hi>Charles,</hi> who ſo Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like expoſed their lives, to aſſiſt at their death thoſe infected with the Plague. I do not mention St. <hi>Francis Xaverius,</hi> who left his Country, Houſe and Hopes, to run to the utmoſt parts of the World after Salvages and Barbarians, to inſtruct them in the knowledge of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And amidſt the deplorable remiſneſs of the Manners of this Age, how many great Intereſts, great Honors, great Reputations, great Hopes, have we ſeen ſacrificed in the generous exerciſe of Chriſtian Charity? How many Perſons of Quality, how many eminent Wits, with ſublime Talents, how many tender and delicate Ladies, have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48587:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubmitted themſelves moſt willingly to the pains of a laborious and obſcure life, to ſuccour their Neighbours? We have ſeen in the old Age of Chriſtianity, and in the corruption of this Age, Apoſtolical Men croſs the Seas, to go and inſtruct Infidels, and bring them into the right way.</p>
               <p>To conclude, this Spirit of the Apoſtles, which God has revived in ſome meaſure in theſe latter Times, and this ſo fervent zeal for the ſalvation of Souls, is ſo apparently the true Spirit of Chriſtianity, and the eſſential diſtinction between the Children of the Church and others which are not of it; That though it be above an Age ſince ſome of our Neighbours, who have unhappily left the Faith, run into all parts of the World, there to plant Traffick and Commerce, which flouriſh amongſt them: yet there has not yet appear'd any one Paſtor of their Communion, that has had the virtue and courage to give his life to Baptize one Salvage, and Convert one Infidel. So true it is, that the diſintereſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and purity of Chriſtian Charity, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo much as counterfeited by Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; who impudently boaſt themſelves to inherit the Faith of the Apoſtles: when in reality they have not any mark of their Zeal, or ſign of their Spirit; ſince they can
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48587:18"/>behold without any concern, the People with whom they Traffick continually, in a profound ignorance of things neceſſary to their ſalvation. For what means the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency of theſe falſe Paſtors, who, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt compaſſion, ſee the Flock of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſcattered and ſtraying? What means this ſo cold tranquility, but what our Lord himſelf ſaid, That the true Paſtor, (whereof himſelf was the Model) is always ready to give his life for his Flock; and that the mercenary Paſtor concerns not himſelf for the Flock of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is an Hireling? Its in Charity then alone conſiſts the true Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity we ſeek after. She is that precious Jewel of the Goſpel, which muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at any rate, to become the truly rich of the new Law. Let us then renounce our Intereſts and Pleaſures, if they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles to our poſſeſſing it. But to animate our ſelves ſtill more to acquire it, let us look into its value, by conſidering its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and qualities. Its that muſt be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the following Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48587:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the nature and qualities of this Charity, in which conſiſts the Spirit of Chriſtianity; and the <hi>Idea</hi> of a Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>'TIS natural for Man to love Man; But 'tis a great vertue to love him for his vertues ſake: for love that is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on honeſty, wiſdom, good inclination, fidelity, or any other real merit, is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and 'tis laudable to love theſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are themſelves worthy of praiſe. But after all, thus to love, is to love but like a Heathen: for the Pagans love thoſe that love them, and ſuch as have qualities worthy their love. What is it then to love like a Chriſtian? 'Tis to love without hearkening to Nature, which wills that we love our like; 'Tis to love, even without conſulting our Reaſon, which requires that we love what is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be beloved. Nature and Reaſon do not comprehend this Secret: The Goſpel muſt ſpeak, and 'tis <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf muſt teach it. To love like a Chriſtian, is to love that which has nothing amiable; 'Tis to have a kindneſs and tenderneſs for thoſe that have all unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48587:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and rigour for us: In fine, to love like a Chriſtian, is to deſire the good of thoſe that wiſh us nothing but ill.</p>
               <p>This Vertue was unknown to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> to Philoſophy and the old Law. The Precept to love our Enemies, is of the new Law; And this ſo holy Maxim could not come but out of the School of God, ſo much 'tis raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Man. 'Tis indeed <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Author of it, and himſelf in Perſon that inſtructs us: <hi>But I ſay to you, love your Enemies, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that calumniate, and perſecute you.</hi> Theſe are the words of the Saviour of the World: Behold our Belief, our Goſpel, our Morality, and the true Character of our Religion. The other marks of a Chriſtian, as Devotion, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Hope in God, Humility, and even Martyrdom it ſelf, may be equivocal marks: 'Tis only the love of our Enemies that is not: 'Tis hereby alone that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can diſtinguiſh himſelf; and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Faith, is to embrace the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to love the Perſecutor, in loving the Perſecution.</p>
               <p>But how can a man love that which merits his hate, when he has ſcacre power to love that which deſerves to be beloved?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48587:19"/>What violence muſt not he uſe to himſelf before he gains that Point? He needs not uſe any; for from the inſtant that he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely becomes a Chriſtian, he loves his Enemies as really as his Friends; And the ſame Motive that makes a Chriſtian love God, the ſame alſo makes him love his Neighbour as a Child of God; for he ſees reflect on him a beam of the ſame light, that makes himſelf know God. Although his Brother be his Enemy; from the time that he regards him as a Member of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſprinkled with his Bloud, fed with his Fleſh, enliven'd with his Spirit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd to his Glory; that he profeſſes the ſame Law and Religion as he do's; that they have both the ſame Hopes, the ſame Pretenſions, the ſame Sacraments; and when he conſiders <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in his Neighbour, as the motive of his Charity, he loves him: And Fleſh, Bloud, Nature, Reaſon, Intereſt, and Paſſion, are too weak Conſiderations to diſunite Hearts tied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by ſo holy an Union; that is to ſay, by all that is ſupernatural and divine in Chriſtianity. So, the motive of the love of our Neighbour being the ſame with the motive of our love of God, as St. <hi>Leo</hi> teacheth; both the one and the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounded on the ſame principle, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48587:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>tending to the ſame end; a Chriſtian can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be failing in the one, without failing in the other; ſince the ſame ray of Faith which enlightens his ſpirit to know God, ought to enflame his heart to love his Neighbour. For with what ſincerity can he boaſt he loves God whom he do's not ſee, and not love his Neighbour whom he ſees, and who repreſents to him that ſame God he boaſts that he loves, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays? Behold what's the nature of Chriſtian Charity, that in effect cannot love her Neighbour, but with the ſame love wherewith ſhe loves God: which made St. <hi>John</hi> ſay, <hi>That he who has cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is in God, and God in him:</hi> Let us then examine the qualities of this Charity.</p>
               <p>The Firſt quality of this Vertue is, that 'tis Univerſal, and cannot ſuffer to be bounded in the extent of its love: for it loves the little and the great, the poor and the rich, the wretched and the happy, the peeviſh and the complaiſant, the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the domeſtick, him that merits to be beloved, and him that deſerves not. Wherein 'tis in ſome ſort like God, <hi>who ſhares his gifts to the worthy and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and pours forth his light on the juſt and unjuſt.</hi> In fine, this Vertue embraces equally the whole World: 'Tis an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48587:20"/>ſpirit, that knows none of thoſe carnal and Heatheniſh diſtinctions, of Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Intereſt, Party, Cabal, of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> which divide at preſent ſo many petty ſpirits in the World. For, according to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> To love all men, and to pretend to except but one, with whom he is not entirely ſatisfied, and not able to bear with for ſome particular reaſons; is not to love like a Chriſtian. A Chriſtian has an univerſal love, becauſe the motive of it is general: the change of Times, Places, and Circumſtances, can make no alteration in his love; he loves in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and health, in adverſity and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in affliction and joy, in humiliation and greatneſs, in dejection and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in poverty and plenty, to be ſhort, he loves in life and in death; becauſe he is that ſincere Friend of whom the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks, <hi>who loves at all times.</hi> He fixes his heart on the Perſons without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the Circumſtances, unleſs it be to love after a more diſintereſſed manner, and when neceſſity more requires it. Behold the firſt quality of Chriſtian Charity.</p>
               <p>The Second is Sincerity: <hi>Let us love,</hi> ſays St. John, <hi>but let us teſtifie our love by effects, and not by words:</hi> The Character of humane Love conſiſts only in Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48587:21"/>Civilities, tender of Services, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of Amity, ſtrain'd Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, falſe Friendſhips, vain Words, deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Promiſes, and in all other Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are commonly practiſed by thoſe that lead a worldly life. But Chriſtian Charity never counterfeits: ſhe ſpeaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what ſhe thinks: ſhe thinks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what ſhe feels, ſhe feels nothing but what ſhe would execute: her words never belie her actions, and her actions are always conformable to her Sentiments; for ſhe is eſſectially ſincere, and has no other way to explain her ſelf, but by her deeds.</p>
               <p>The Third quality of this Vertue, is Purity of ſpirit, and a perfect diſintereſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: for true Charity reſpects God alone, and ſtudies purely to pleaſe him: ſo as ſhe never acts upon thoſe mean and worldly Conſiderations of Intereſt and Vanity, which ſet men awork: for Men do ſeldom good to one another, but out of hopes of Intereſt. 'Tis on theſe Maxims they would have all the World know when they do their Friend any ſervice; they are only of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious to gain repute; and oblige only to publiſh it: If they are ſilent, 'tis for ſome private reaſon that they ſee it fit to hold their tongue. Chriſtian Charity has a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary way of proceeding to this worldly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48587:21"/>Charity: ſhe has no other deſign or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, becauſe her motive is pure. All her ſtudy in doing good, is how to conceal her doing it: If ſhe gives Alms, ſhe hides them in the Laps of the Poor, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſays; ſhe draws a Veil over all her good Deeds, that they may not be known, and ſhe would hide them even from her own ſelf, were it poſſible, to entruſt them only to her modeſty and ſilence. The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhe takes in doing good is to her a greater recompence, then all the applauſes of Men. As ſhe do's nothing but for God, ſo ſhe would have no other witneſs of her actions. He is the ſole motive of the good works ſhe do's; and it ſuffices he knows them, to be himſelf their recompence.</p>
               <p>The other qualities of Charity St. <hi>Paul</hi> explicates in the admirable Elogy he made of this Vertue to the <hi>Corinthians: Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> (ſays this Apoſtle) <hi>is patient, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign. Charity envies not, deals not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly, is not puffed up, is not ambitious, ſeeks not her own, is not provoked to anger, thinks not evil, rejoyces not upon iniquity, but rejoyces with the truth, ſuffers all things, believes all things, hopes all things, bears all things:</hi> Theſe qualities become yet more luſtrous in the life of a Chriſtian, which is a continual practiſe and exerciſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48587:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>of this Vertue. 'Tis good to make hereof ſome Idea, only to ſhew what it is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to our Neighbours: The lineaments of ſo admirable a picture, which length of time has almoſt decay'd, cannot be well tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced over again, without gathering thence ſome profit.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian is altogether an interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Man, who has nothing of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Man in us, but the outward ſhape: but there appears ſo much of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and wiſdom even in his exteriour, and Gods Grace has ſo powerfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd his natural inclinations, to ſanctifie all his interiour, that he is a pattern to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, becauſe he is more reaſonable, and better govern'd then other men. His chief character is the ſpirit of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And of all Vertues, Juſtice is that which he moſt accuſtoms himſelf to, becauſe ſhe always ſerves him to hold the ballance even betwixt himſelf and his Neighbour. His buſineſs is not to raiſe his fortune, but his perfection, and to help others to make themſelves perfect: And his ordinary employment is to inſtruct, help, protect, and ſerve his Brethren: but he do's it with ſo much love, ſo much zeal, and ſo much diſintereſſedneſs; that there is no man loves himſelf ſo well, as a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48587:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtian loves his Neighbour. His Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours intereſt is more dear to him then his own: and he is leſs concern'd for his own honour then his Brethrens; for he counts their advantages among his own, he draws his ſatisfaction from their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: And by an unparalell'd compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency he transforms himſelf into their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and aſſumes ſometimes even their ſpirit. He is that univerſal Man, who, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is every thing to every one: He is the comfort of the afflicted, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the feeble, the ſuccour of the needy, the refuge of the perſecuted, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of all thoſe that want it. In fine, there is no weakneſs that he do's not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate, and no miſery at which his bowels are not moved. He is ſo far from deſiring what he has not, like the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of men, that he is always ready to give what he has. If modeſty appears in his Dreſs, frugality at his Table, ſimplicity in his Houſhold-ſtuff, and good Husbandry throughout; 'tis but, by his contempt of luxury, to ſave wherewithal he may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the neceſſity of the Poor, to whom he gives his helping hand in all their wants. His Eſtate is the Poor's, becauſe their poverty is his.</p>
               <p>The ſole luſtre of Charity ſhines in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48587:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing he do's, without any mixture of the leaſt ſmoke of vanity. His modeſty throws out all Sentiments of his own glory, and he knows no other but that of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, and obliging all the world: So that he do's not heap up Wealth to enrich him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but therewith to do good to others: 'Tis not to be knowing he ſtudies, but to ſerve thoſe that are not: He has Riches only for the Poor, and Learning for the Ignorant. Nor is it for himſelf that he is powerful, wiſe, underſtanding, and ready at Buſineſs, but only that by theſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he may be more beneficial to his Neighbour: And he has no ſagacity, but the better to diſcern the ſpirit of others, and to look on them on the more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſide. Though amongſt the proud he has the ſimplicity of the Dove, yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the wicked and impious, according to the counſel of the Goſpel, he has the prudence of the Serpent. He knows how to make advantage of their defects, and the depravedneſs of the moſt corrupted ſpirits ſerve him for inſtructions; for by their weakneſs he regulates his power.</p>
               <p>When he is rais'd in Dignity, and his Deſerts have plac'd him above his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to govern them; Then is he like the good Paſtor of the Goſpel, who felt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48587:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>more grief for the ſtraying of one of his Sheep, then joy for being Maſter of a whole Flock. He always looks on a ſinner with a Father-like eye, he bewails him in his diſorders, he ſuffers him with patience, and treats him with mildneſs, not oppreſſing him with the weight of his Authority, that is already overwhelm'd with the preſſure of his Crime: He is tender-hearted and compaſſionate even when his Duty obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges him to be harſh and ſevere. His ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities are far more amiable then the careſſes of others; for when he puniſhes, he do's not heed ſo much the puniſhment of the Offence, as the correction of the Offender. So that in his height in reſpect of other Men, he is like the Candle in the Goſpel, which enlightens the whole Houſe. His carriage is the model of Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, and his life a publick inſtruction for all vertuous People.</p>
               <p>He firſt impoſes on himſelf the whole weight of that yoke which he is oblig'd to impoſe on others; and as zeal in words becomes fruitleſs, if not ſupported by that of actions, himſelf practices by an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary life, what he would perſwade others. Whatever outrage is done him, cannot make him hate the doer. He underſtands not returnng injury for injury, nor knows
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48587:24"/>what anger is; and he is ſo much maſter of his reſentments, when any injuſtice is done him, that he finds it far leſs difficult to forget, then to remember the offence. But nothing ſhews ſo much his dominion over his own heart, as the quiet he enjoys in the general agitation and heat which other men diſcover in their Affairs. His mildneſs, his patience, his innocence, and his ſincerity, are then all the crafts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks he uſes. His conſcience is not only clear in reſpect of the intereſts he has to determine with others: but his heart clean in the judgment he makes of them; for he judges every thing without prejudice: All appears innocent to him, becauſe all he do's is without deceit. In fine, his chief care is to preſerve an equality of mind, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the inequalities of the Affairs of the World: which concern him no farther, then the connexion they have with the glory of God, or ſalvation of his Neighbour.</p>
               <p>Behold what it is to be a Chriſtian: and not to counterfeit unſeaſonably the zealot about the carriage of others; to be very ſolicitous for their perfection, and careleſs for ones own; to trouble ones head for them, and never think of ones ſelf; to talk of nothing but the primitive Faithful, cite nothing but the ancient Canons, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48587:24"/>deplore the remiſneſs of the Church: Nor is it in the refinements of Diſcipline and Reformation which ſound ſo big every where, or in thoſe intrigues of diſſembled Devotion, in which they place the Vertue of this Age, that the Spirit of Chriſtianity conſiſts. The true Chriſtian is a Man ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, retired, little in his own eyes, which he keeps always as open and obſervant of his own weakneſſes, as cloſed againſt thoſe of others. He takes not any notice of his own advantages, he only obſerves thoſe of his Neighbour: becauſe he has only a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for himſelf, and eſteem and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for others. His conduct edifies all the world, and angers no body: He flies all plauſibleneſs even in good works; becauſe whatever gains credit is dangerous to Man, who is ſubject to miſtake himſelf: He is no backbiter, nor peeviſh; no Man of artifice, no doer of ſhrewd turns. Thus were the Primitive Chriſtians: Nor is this a vain or fruitleſs Idea of a Chriſtian, or his Character that I have drawn: for the Chriſtians lived after this manner in the newneſs of ſpirit of the Primitive Church. What, is this Image entirely defaced? and is this Spirit retir'd wholly from us? Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Times when they lived thus! when will you return? But it is not enough to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48587:25"/>know wherein Chriſtian Charity conſiſts; what its nature and qualities are: if the art how to practiſe it be unknown.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the true practice of Charity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Spirit of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</head>
               <p>THere is no Vertue of a more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal uſe in Chriſtianity, then Charity: It may be practiſed on all occaſions, for the Poor are found every where; and the detail of miſeries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Man is ſubject, is of ſo vaſt extent, that one may ſay 'tis of all Conditions. Thus Charity may be exerciſed to the Rich and Poor, to the contented and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, to the happy and unhappy, to the learned and ignorant, to the proud and humble, to the living and dead. So that this Vertue may be practiſed in publick and private, in the light and in the dark, at home and abroad, in the Court and the Deſart, in ſolitude and Aſſemblies; and of all Conditions that's moſt deſirable to a Chriſtian wherein he has the beſt means
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48587:25"/>to exerciſe Charity: as of all Talents that's the moſt advantageous, which is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to ones Neighbour.</p>
               <p>The better to diſpoſe ones ſelf to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe this Vertue, he ought to begin with ſtudying the miſeries of Man, which are its chiefeſt object: He ought to ſearch into the bottom of his nothingneſs, to know the baſeneſs of his beginning, the ſhamefulneſs of his birth, the poverty of his nature, the infirmities of his infancy, the paſſions of his youth, the caducity of his old age: To theſe ought be added the diſeaſes and illneſſes, the pains, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities, the fatigues, the accidents, and other miſeries to which his Body is ſubject. The miſeries of his Spirit are ſtill greater; What ignorance, what blindneſs, what errors, what doubts, what contradictions in his deſigns, what praeoccupation in his thoughts, what falſeneſs in his judgments? What ſhall I ſay of his levities, inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, irreſolutions, frailties, diſſimulations, niceneſſes, and riots? There may be added to the heap of his other weakneſſes, the diſcontents and chagrins that devour him, the cares that diſtract him, the afflictions that oppreſs him, his own deſires that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, the great propenſity he has to evil, and his inability to do good; his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48587:26"/>falls and relapſes, the number and enormity of his crimes, his abuſe of graces, the irregularity of his conduct, and the general diſorder of his whole life. In fine, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſays, Man is nothing but indigency, corruption, and miſery. Behold the firſt ground on which the Charity of a Chriſtian ought to apply his aſſiſtance according to the diſcretion of his zeal, and as his Neighbours neceſſity requires.</p>
               <p>But his firſt care ought to be directed to the more apparent neceſſities, and which are obvious of themſelves, without his ſeeking after them. As to give Bread to him that has none, to cloath the naked, to help the ſick, and to viſit the impriſoned. His ſuperfluities may ſupply him for theſe aſſiſtances; and he will always have them, if he regulates his vanity, and lives accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſpirit of the Goſpel. After all, if he has little, let him give little, if he has much, let him give much, according as <hi>Tobias</hi> adviſes; for the Riches one has ought to be the meaſure of his Alms. I need not mention thoſe that voluntarily become poor, profeſſing to imitate the poverty of our Lord: Every one knows what preference they ought to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others when Alms are diſtributed; becauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to whom they are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48587:26"/>given, is more remarkable in them then in others.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe viſible neceſſities, which all the world ſees, there are divers others that are more concealed, which the ſhame of thoſe that feel them hides from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the moſt charitable: for there are many, that chuſe rather to be miſerable, then to declare their miſeries. But Charity when induſtrious, quickly knows how to find out theſe wants, let them be never ſo ſecret, and when faithful to provide for them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> too, deſires a Chriſtian ſhould participate with his Brother in his joy when he is pleaſed, and in his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure when otherwiſe; he would have him troubled or quiet, according as his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is, and that he ſhould ſhare in his Sentiments as well as his Intereſts. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding becauſe there are wants more important then temporal ones, a Chriſtian is alſo oblig'd to more preſſing and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Duties of Charity; which are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for ſpiritual neceſſities: the extent whereof is immenſe, by reaſon of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Man's mind; and Man being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſo many miſeries, a Chriſtian, if he be deſirous to live like one, will never want occaſions to exerciſe his Charity. For ſometimes he'l be oblig'd by his mildneſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48587:27"/>and patience, to reduce him that is ſtray'd, into the way of Vertue; he'l ſtrengthen the weak, he'l ſtir up the ſlothful, he'l en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the fearful, he'l ſettle the diſquiets of a fleeting and irreſolute mind: Then again, by the ſeverity of his Diſcourſe, he'l frighten the obſtinate, and by the terror of his threats reclaim the pride of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous and intractable. Another time he'l make the humble comprehend to encourage him, that the kingdom of heaven is his inheritance, becauſe he is the true poor of ſpirit to whom the Goſpel promiſes it: and he will open the eyes of the afflicted, to make him ſee plainly that crown promis'd to him, who ſhall have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the trial of tribulation. He'l teach the covetous not to fix his heart on the periſhable vain things of this world. He'l inſtruct the voluptuous how to reſiſt his ſenſual appetite. He'l overthrow the deceitful peace of the wiſe worldling, who puts his confidence in the prudence of the fleſh. He'l awake him that's doz'd in ſin, by the wholſom terrors of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: By the ſolidity of his Diſcourſe he'l deſtroy the falſe reaſonings of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious; And by the ſincerity and diſinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſedneſs of his carriage ſilence the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, when he ſhall have the impudence to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48587:27"/>call him hypocrite and diſſembler, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the unhappy language of this Age, where impiety, to ſignalize it ſelf, has found the art to confound true Vertue with falſe, thereby to diminiſh her cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; becauſe the very example of Vertue becomes troubleſom and vexatious to ſuch as live licentiouſly.</p>
               <p>But, when his Brother, who is unjuſtly oppreſt, ſhall have his heart overcharg'd with grief, he'l find ſome means to eaſe him of this weight, either by the aid of ſome wholſom counſel, or the mildneſs of ſome charitable comfort, that ſo he may prevent his deſpair. He'l inſtruct, even by his example, all that ſuffer, to ſubmit to the ſevereſt diſpoſitions of Providence, and with reſignation to ſuffer thoſe amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous chaſtiſements which the hand of God is pleas'd to inflict. He'l alſo accuſtom himſelf not eaſily to be ſhock'd, as many are, at the defects of others; Nay he'l find by uſing himſelf to that, 'tis more wit and vertue to comply with them, then to pleaſe himſelf in the good qualities of thoſe he converſes with. To be the child of peace in the Goſpel, fit to reconcile thoſe whom animoſity or hatred imbitter to one another, let him not be raſh in his judgments, let him avoid even the ſhadow
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48587:28"/>of the leaſt ſuſpicion, let him never heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to detraction and calumny; and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf againſt falſe impreſſions, let him never aſſent to any thing ſpoken to the diſadvantage of others before he has examin'd it, nor condemn any upon the ill conſtruction of his intentions.</p>
               <p>When by the Functions of his Charge, or the pure duty of Charity, he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to puniſh; let him remember that the ſpirit of ſweetneſs and mildneſs, is the firſt Character of a Chriſtian, and that ſeverity is a miſtaken vertue, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then on the principle of Charity. True Charity is humble and patient even in choler it ſelf, and is tender and mild in ſeverity. If he muſt admoniſh and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, let a Chriſtian firſt know the ſecret how to ſweeten his admonitions, and clear his reprehenſions of all that's harſh and vexatious, and let him mix withal thoſe inſinuating ways which are neceſſary to gain him, whom one would not have loſt. Let him excuſe all but ſin, which, once known, is inexcuſable. The force and kindneſs, wherewith our Lord excuſed <hi>Magdalen</hi> againſt the reproaches of the Phariſee, ought to inſtruct us, that in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain occaſions, we ought to have kindneſs to bear with a ſinner, and force to defend him.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48587:28"/>
               <p>But as the World places its Morality in not pardoning, by making Revenge a Vertue; and the higheſt pitch of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian perfection is to love our Enemies: Herein it is a Chriſtian ought moſt to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize himſelf. Philoſophy has not yet been able to reach ſo far, and it is the greateſt difficulty in Chriſtianity to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it. But after that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has both by his Doctrine and Example taught us his intentions on that Point, a Chriſtian, who will live like one, ought to lay aſide his reſentments, and weakneſſes, to pardon any injury done him. 'Tis confeſs'd, the Heathens have own'd ſome ſhadow of this Vertue, amidſt the darkneſs of their Morals, and there appears ſome rough draughts of it, in their moſt illuſtrious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but after all, 'twas only out of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that they pardoned: Their clemency was only a ſecret pride, whereby they ſought after applauſe and reputation. On the contrary, Chriſtian clemency flies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as vanity, and only ſeeks the intereſt and advantage of whom ſhe pardons.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, there is another ſort of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be practiſed; more perfect then the others, in regard 'tis more pure and diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed: for it is without hope of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48587:29"/>ſince it is done for the Dead, by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting with our Prayers thoſe holy Souls, which ſuffer in <hi>Purgatory</hi> through thoſe painful inquietudes, and grievous impatien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies they have, to ſee themſelves ſeparated from God. Theſe are the Creatures of all the world the moſt afflicted, through the cruel torments they ſuffer; and withal the moſt worthy to be ſuccour'd: for what are not they worthy of, that are che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht and predeſtinated by God? What glory is it for a Chriſtian to be Mediator between God, and theſe holy Souls, who ceaſe not to love him, though they ſuffer all the rigor of his Juſtice, and to adore even his chaſtiſements, and vengeances? 'Tis even (if we may ſo ſay) to do God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a pleaſure to ſuccour theſe Souls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loves them; and his Juſtice is better ſatisfied with our Prayers, then their Sufferings, becauſe our Prayers are volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and their Sufferings not: And thus the Charity of the Living, eaſes and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Pains of the Dead.</p>
               <p>But if it be ſo great a Charity, to help the Souls that are but for ſome time ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from God; what will it be then, to be aſſiſting to ſinners, who through their criminal engagements, are in danger to be eternally ſeparated from him? Theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48587:29"/>wretches do not conſider, in how deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a condition they are; and that 'tis the greateſt madneſs and blindneſs to prefer a momentary pleaſure before their ſalvation: how great Charity is it to make them comprehend this? But what patience, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, prudence and great circumſpection needs there to effect it? 'Tis a ſecret, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Directors ſcarce remember, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix a Fatherly connivance and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with theſe ſo neceſſary medicinal ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gors, for the cure of a ſinner ſeduced by his ignorance, and abandon'd to his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. One muſt ſtudy the diſpoſition, the habitudes, the inclinations of his Penitent, and obſerve the way of entring into his heart, to exerciſe there abſolutely this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſeverity which cures the Soul. But they ſeldom give themſelves this trouble: this mixture of authority and love, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and compliance, of zeal and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, of mildneſs and auſterity, are ſcarce any longer uſed in Direction; the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is precipitated either by compoſition, or by a falſe principle of rigor to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſevere; becauſe the World reliſhes that beſt. This capacity of a Doctor, this prudence of a Phyſician, theſe bowels of a Father, and this diſintereſſedneſs of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> are qualities rarely
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48587:30"/>found in one and the ſame Perſon, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him a perfect Director. In chuſing one, ſuch as authorize ſin by their ſoftneſs, in flattering a ſinner by too much compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and thoſe, who by their ſeverities diſproportion'd to the weakneſs of their Penitents ſerve only to diſcourage them, are alike to be avoided; for they are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dangerous.</p>
               <p>I have ſtuck a little upon this Point: for 'tis in this Chriſtian Charity may be beſt exerciſed, and wherein generally 'tis leaſt practiſed; becauſe we are not ſufficiently toucht with the deplorable condition of a ſinner. Although at this day there's more pretending to Direction then ever, yet we ſcarce ſee any longer thoſe zealous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors, who are Chriſtianly obſtinate to diſarm the anger of God againſt ſinners by the auſterity of their lives, and who draw down the graces of God upon their Penitents, by the perſeverance of their Prayers and Mortifications. 'Tis to theſe charitable Directors we owe thoſe great Converſions, which God makes be ſeen from time to time, as ſtriking rays of his mercy. Theſe are the ordinary fruits wherewith God takes pleaſure to bleſs the voluntary Penances and Mortifications of thoſe vertuous innocent Souls, who in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48587:30"/>ſecret of their hearts deplore the ſins of their Brethren: which ought to be a great comfort to thoſe Chriſtians whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat deprives them of the other occaſions to exerciſe Charity. For a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> a <hi>Carmelite,</hi> a Monk the moſt retired from commerce with Men, may ſometimes do as much good at the foot of his Crucifix, in aſſiſting his Neighbour by the inviſible help of his Prayers, as the moſt eloquent Preachers, the moſt zealous Miſſioners, and and all thoſe whoſe Profeſſion engages them to ſerve the Publick in the direction of Souls. Beſides 'tis always leſs dangerous, and often more profitable, to ſpeak of Men to God in ſecret Prayer, then to ſpeak of God to Men in the ſhew and tumult of Preaching.</p>
               <p>I ſay nothing of that eminent Charity practiſed heretofore by the Apoſtles in the primitive Times of Grace: which the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World prefers before all other Charities; becauſe by a generous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of death ſhe willingly offers up her life for the ſalvation of her Neighbour. I believ'd I even ought not to ſpeak of it, becauſe the exerciſe of this Chatity is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Rules, and beſides 'tis one of thoſe extraordinary graces God only beſtows on his favourites: Not but that in theſe latter
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48587:31"/>Times ſome ſparks of that ſacred fire are ſeen ſhining ſtill in Apoſtolical Men, who travel to the fartheſt parts of the World, to water thoſe barren and ingrateful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions with their ſweat, and even their bloud, to draw down on them the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Heaven, and make Chriſtianity flouriſh there; but every one do's not partake of theſe graces, theſe are the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, and theſe mercies are great miracles. Let us adore the deſigns of God in thoſe to whom he do's theſe favours; and let us bleſs him for vouchſafing to caſt his eyes on them, to allow them the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to die for him. Happy he, who in guiding of Souls merits to ſuffer at leaſt ſome ſmall perſecution, though he be not worthy at the expence of his life to ſerve his Neighbour! Happy he, who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute his tears and ſighs to the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Heathens, when he cannot his bloud and life! It ought to be the moſt ordinary Devotion of all good people to ſigh before God, and to offer him vows for the ſalvation of all men; that the Death of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> may not be fruitleſs to them. For the true Chriſtian ought not to confine the whole extent of his zeal within the narrow circle of his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: he ought to labour for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48587:31"/>and ſalvation of others. If his Faith be ſo fervent, and his Prayer ſo humble and perſeverant as it ought to be, for ſo important a ſubject; what fruit may he not hope? This every one may pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: and the precious Bloud of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> which (in thoſe Countries where he is not known) loſes its value, well deſerves that a Chriſtian zealous for his glory ſhould affect ſo holy and charitable a Devotion.</p>
               <p>Behold, throughout the whole Diſcourſe I have made, there's a large way lies open for Chriſtian Charity, to exerciſe ſo many different good works as concern it. But there remains one work of Charity for a Chriſtian to practiſe, ſo much the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier to be recommended to him, as no body is aware to think of it: 'Tis, to pray often to God for the ſalvation of the Great ones, and for all thoſe, whom Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence abandons to the vanity of worldly Honors, and the covetouſneſs of Riches. Man being always weaker in elevation, and proſperity, then in depreſſion, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; the greater he is, the more worthy of compaſſion. For Greatneſs is a Shelf, ſo much the more dangerous, as its appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is more deceitful. It is not the voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian to be always happy, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48587:32"/>ſucceſsful: and it often happens that God, through a terrible order of his Providence, gives up theſe worldly happy ones, to the wandring of their hearts, and, by a ſecret Judgment, ſuffers them to fall into a blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and obſtinacy, which renders them inſenſible of all the motions of Grace, and all the inſpirations of Heaven.</p>
               <p>If we have Charity, let us tremble for thoſe that are in ſo ſad a condition; Let us implore Gods mercy upon the miſery of thoſe falſlly happy ones; Let us give the Potentates of the Earth the ſame counſel as <hi>Daniel</hi> heretofore gave unto one of the greateſt Princes of the World: <hi>To redeem their injuſtices by deeds of mercy, and to blot out their ſins by alms.</hi> Let us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make Great men underſtand that God beſtows neither Greatneſs nor Power on them to live in pleaſure and delicacies; that their being rais'd to Offices obliges them more ſtrictly to be watchful and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious; that they have no Power and Authority but to aſſiſt more powerfully him that is weak, and deliver him from the oppreſſion of the ſtrong. Let us put them in mind that they are not great in the ſight of God, but in as much as they are beneficial and helpful to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; that the luſtre of temporal Honors,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48587:32"/>and all theſe external Greatneſſes are but marks of their Servitude, and continual remembrances of their Duties; That Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities ought to have no place in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but more to ſet off the Chriſtian; That the Great ones can pretend to Heaven only by their Alms, for they are ſcarce ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any other good; That God, who has no exception of perſons, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſays, will have no reſpect to their Quality, but only to their good works and their Charity, when they ſhall appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Throne. This is what may in ſhort be ſaid of the practice of this Vertue, whoſe extent is beyond meaſure; But it is not ſufficient to know how it ought to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, unleſs we alſo know what method to obſerve in the practice of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> In what order Chriſtian Charity ought to be practiſed.</head>
               <p>AS the whole perfection of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity may be ſaid to conſiſt in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo this Vertue ought to be the moſt regulated of all Chriſtian Vertues, becauſe this is the Rule of all the Duties of a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48587:33"/>Chriſtian. So there is nothing ſo eſſential to Charity, as order: But there's nothing more difficult then preciſely to eſtabliſh that order wherein Charity ought to be practis'd. For beſides that every one, in the exerciſe of Chriſtian Vertue, frames ſeveral Principles to himſelf according to his own fancy or reaſon; and that thence comes the great diverſity of ways we meet with in a ſpiritual Life: Charity beſides of her ſelf, in the extent of the divers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of our Neighbour, obliges a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to ſo many different Duties, that 'tis difficult to give any exact Rule for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing them juſtly. This Vertue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes raſh and indiſcreet if not govern'd by Prudence: and Charity without this Prudence, which is her principal guide, is not a true Charity. The more fervent the Zeal is, and the more active the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the more ſhe needs this ſcience, which knows, ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> how to huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band its heat. 'Tis for this reaſon that the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> gives thanks to her Bridegroom; <hi>becauſe he had regulated in her the Duties of Charity.</hi> Let us then ſeek out this Rule ſo neceſſary to this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to diſtinguiſh its obligations; and let us examine the order wherein it muſt be practiſed: that ſo the eſſential Duties
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48587:33"/>may not be confounded with thoſe that are not.</p>
               <p>The firſt draught of this order ought to be taken from the Goſpel, wherein our Saviour himſelf has laid the model by his own Example: when he forbad his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to go Preach to the <hi>Samaritans</hi> and Gentiles, till they had Preach'd firſt to the Jews; and when he refuſed that help the <hi>Cananean</hi> Woman (S. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſpeaks of) begg'd of him, becauſe ſhe was a ſtranger, and he would reſerve his favours for his own People, like a Paſtor who minds only his own Flock. The Apoſtles did the ſame: there appears a diſtinction in their carriage. They Preach'd not to the Gentiles, till the Jews had refuſed to hear them, according as their Maſter had order'd them: and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the greatneſs of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s zeal to announce <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to the whole World, yet all the motions of that zeal were regulated: He goes not indifferently to all the World; his firſt care was of the Jews, whereever he found any of them in all his Voyages, and he minded not the Converſion of the Heathens, till he had try'd in vain all ways to gain thoſe People whence he ſprang.</p>
               <p>This conduct remarks to us in general that there are diſtinctions to be made in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48587:34"/>the practice of Charity; where three Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties may be found. The Firſt is to know what ſide to take, when the intereſt of God and our Neighbour come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Second is to ſeparate our own intereſts from our Neighbours. The Third is in the different intereſts of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to know which to prefer before the other. Behold, methinks the order that Charity preſcribes in theſe encounters, and the Rules that may be given of it.</p>
               <p>The Firſt Rule, which regards the order to be obſerv'd in the Affairs that concern the intereſt of God and our Neighbour to carry our ſelves duly between one and the other, is of greateſt importance in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Life. The concurrence of theſe two intereſts is often very prejudicial to the zeal of Charity when not back'd with ſcience: for oftentimes we inconſiderately forſake our Neighbour, when we ought to leave God; and we leave God, when we ought to forſake our Neighbour. See then how St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> adviſes us to deport our ſelves: <hi>The obligation</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to love God, in the order of the Precept, ought to precede the obligation to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; but God will have us, in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, prefer our Neighbour before him.</hi> In effect, <hi>It is not reaſonable</hi> (ſays this great
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48587:34"/>Saint) <hi>that God, who is the Maſter and ordains all things, ſhould put himſelf after our Neighbour in the order of Love;</hi> This is the Firſt Command he gave Man, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, and thou ſhalt love him withal thy heart.</hi> But this ſame God, though he be Maſter, yet when our Neighbours good comes in queſtion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſomething of his own right as to its execution. If any coldneſs has paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and our Brethren, wherein our Union may be wounded, and we are at the foot of his Altars to render God the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage due unto him: He then commands us to interrupt his Worſhip, and ſuſpend the moſt holy and auguſt Ceremonies of Religion; to defer till another time the Honors of the Sacrifice we were about to pay him, and firſt go and reconcile our ſelves to our Neighbour. Let them quit, ſays he, the Worſhip they are rendring to me, and the Sacrifice they are offering up; becauſe the Union among Brethren is the moſt agreeable Sacrifice they can offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. He do's even conſent that to help the Poor in their greateſt miſeries we ſhould disfurniſh his very Altars of their outward Ornaments, which are only of uſe to move the groſs Devotion of carnal People, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſays; who condemns the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48587:35"/>of thoſe that enrich the Temples of God, and abandon the Poor.</p>
               <p>What folly (ſays he) is it to leave the Children of the Church naked, and to adorn the Walls ſo magnificently with Tapeſtries and other more precious Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? 'Tis true, the Church may admit Ornaments in her abundance and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: But God commands her to relieve the Poor, who are her Children, when in neceſſity and publick miſeries; becauſe her Treaſures and Riches would only ſerve to ſhame her, if the Poor were not ſuccour'd therewith. This Rule will appear of a very large extent, to ſuch as take pains to conſider it; and the practice of it will be found of much uſe, when apply'd to the ſeveral occaſions that may offer themſelves. But ſince God through his ſignal good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will have us to love our Neighbour for the love of him: 'tis but juſt we ſhould ſo govern this love, that if exteriourly we give our charitable help to our Brethren, at leaſt the intention of our heart, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſign of our ſpirit, be all for God: That <hi>we love our Friend in God, and our Enemy for the love of God, which is the right practice of Charity,</hi> as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> teaches it.</p>
               <p>The Second Rule ought to be made uſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48587:35"/>of to diſtinguiſh every ones perſonal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts from thoſe of his Neighbour, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide what of right belongs to each. The Rule I have ſettled may ſerve for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For if God himſelf do's often yield his right where our Neighbour is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, I have the greater reaſon to yield up mine on the like occaſions. But becauſe this Rule is not general, but limited to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Conjunctures, we muſt ſeek for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more univerſal. The Goſpel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me to treat my Neighbour as my ſelf, ſince he ought to be as dear to me as my ſelf; but it do's not command me to yield to him when our intereſts ſhock one another; And in other reſpects there is a natural equity which teaches me to keep my own, by inſtructing me to diſcharge my ſelf of what belongs not to me. There are likewiſe certain intereſts of Honor which I ought to defend againſt my Neighbour who would diſhonor me: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Honor is a <hi>Depoſitum</hi> God has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted to me, which ought to be as dear to me as that of my life; and becauſe he would ſcandalize the World by diſhonoring me. But are there any occaſions wherein I am oblig'd to abandon mine own intereſts, and ſacrifice them to my Neighbour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Reputation by renouncing my own, and to die to ſave his life?</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:48587:36"/>
               <p>'Tis evident that Goods purely tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral being of an inferior order to ſpiritual, when the ſalvation of our Neighbour is concern'd, which is a ſpiritual intereſt, one is oblig'd to abandon his temporal; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſalvation of ones Soul is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all the Goods of the Earth, which are periſhable and corruptible. Thus nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Honor nor Wealth ought to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued when the ſalvation of a Soul is in queſtion. Now 'tis certain, that a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is oblig'd, by the Maxims of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion he profeſſes, to relieve his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in an extream neceſſity of life, which is a temporal good, not only out of his own ſuperfluities, but even what is neceſſary for himſelf. Chriſtian perfection goes yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, teaching a Chriſtian that he ought not only to be ſevere to himſelf, in tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and compaſſion to his Brother, and deprive himſelf to accommodate him of what is commodious and neceſſary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but even to give his liberty, his honor and life, to preſerve the life, honor and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of his Neighbour. In fine, he ought to do that for him, which the Saviour of the World did for us: for how many have there been, that have imitated <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the practice of ſo generous, ſo pure, and ſo diſintereſſed a Charity? But
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48587:36"/>theſe are the wonders of Chriſtian Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and greateſt Miracles of our Holy Religion. Theſe Examples are rather to be admired, then Rules to be indiſpenſably followed, and Duties of obligation to be practiſed.</p>
               <p>The Third Rule is, the order that ought to be obſerv'd in the different intereſts of our Neighbour; that ſo the impulſes of Charity may be followed without miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and that in two wants, either of the ſame or a different nature, we may know which to prefer. In the order of temporal goods Charity always flies to aſſiſt the more urgent wants: for amongſt the afflicted, ſhe runs to him that ſuffers moſt; and ſhe leaves him again if his wants be but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, to aſſiſt him that is in manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his ſalvation. Such was heretofore the conduct of the Apoſtles, who in the infancy of the Church abandon'd the care of temporal neceſſities to attend to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; in quitting the diſtribution of Alms to be vacant to preaching the Word of God: becauſe they eſteemed the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Soul more important then that of the Body. So the care a Chriſtian takes to teach and inſtruct a poor body is more meritorious before God, then what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed to deliver him from miſery: So the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48587:37"/>Alms given to convert people to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> are far preciouſer, then thoſe which are given for their ſubſiſtance; and the ſweats, pains and fatigues of the Miſſioners who go to preach the Word of God to Infidels in the remoteſt Countries, are of far more value, then the Treaſures that are ſent thither. The ſoveraign perfection of Chriſtian Charity is the fervent zeal of theſe holy Followers of the Apoſtles, who quit all, to ſeek in the moſt ſalvage and barbarous Climates the ſtray Sheep, and to ſatisfie the thirſt and hunger they have for the ſalvation of ſo many abandon'd people, to make them know <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and to bring them back to his Flock.</p>
               <p>In theſe concurrences of wants, Charity ought to diſpoſe of her help, according to the different degrees of neceſſities ſhe finds. But when the want is equal in two different perſons, It is, ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> either Proximity of Bloud, or Alliance, or Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Neighbourhood, or Society, or Country, or the Conſiderations of other Ties that muſt regulate the preference of aſſiſtance due to one rather then to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For although <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> be come into the World to make, by the Sword of Chriſtianity, diviſion betwixt the Fleſh and the Spirit: yet he is not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48587:37"/>the Duties of Bloud, and to diſpence with a Chriſtian for what he ows his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; becauſe theſe Duties are grounded on Equity, which is their principal foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. Thus, what we owe to our Kindred is of a more ſtrict obligation, then that which is due to an unknown Perſon and a Stranger: So a Paſtor is more oblig'd to his Flock, a Superior to thoſe whom God has put under him, a Prince to his own Subjects, then to all others; and in the order of Chriſtian Charity a Friend ought to be more dear then one unknown, a Domeſtick then a Stranger, and a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian then an Infidel; and when they are both equally in need, you are oblig'd to help the one before the other. This Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality is founded on Juſtice and Reaſon, which orders it thus; and on the conduct of our Lord, who carried himſelf after this manner between the Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus inſtructs Chriſtians, St. <hi>Thomas</hi> and all Catholick Divines are of this opinion: For the reſt, when the Rules I have eſtabliſh'd are duly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 'twill be found that our Soul, being our Neighbour a thouſand times more intimate then our deareſt Friends or our neareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, our firſt obligation is to exerciſe Charity towards her; which we cannot do
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48587:38"/>as we ought, but by endeavouring her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection preferably above all things. For if we neglect her, who will take care of her? And if we give all but our ſelves to God, is not that to keep our ſelves the better ſhare? becauſe God will have us our ſelves, and not what is ours: as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſays.</p>
               <p>The concluſion of this Diſcourſe is, that extream neceſſity in temporals, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a Soul in ſpirituals, ought to have preference in the ſtricteſt obligations of a Chriſtian. So that the moſt laudable and holy of all Charities is to provide for ſpiritual wants; as to procure aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for People who are in a deep igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of all things relating to their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and without help: But in aſſiſting Aliens and Salvages, muſt thoſe be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that live in the midſt of us, and are in the ſame wants? can we hearken to what's told us of the miſeries of Perſons of another World, as one may ſay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beholding what we daily ſee amongſt thoſe we know? It is this obliges me to repeat, what I have already ſaid, and which is ſo important that it cannot be too often repeated: That the greateſt Zeal requires the greateſt Knowledge: That if Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prudence ought to be animated by Charity, Charity ought to be govern'd by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48587:38"/>Prudence; and juſtly to diſcern the order wherein Charity ought to be practiſed, nothing more needs to be recommended to a Chriſtian, then what the Apoſtle recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to thoſe of the City of <hi>Philippi,</hi> to whom he Preach'd this Vertue, <hi>That their Charity may more and more abound in knowledge and in all underſtanding:</hi> To be neither indiſcreet, nor raſh; becauſe the greateſt defect in Charity is want of light, which renders this Vertue ſubject to an infinity of Illuſions. But intirely to purifie its practice, 'tis beſt to diſcover the Illuſions, that ſo they may be diſſipated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the ſeveral Illuſions to which the Practice of Charity is ſubject.</head>
               <p>ALL Chriſtian Vertues are in their Practice ſubject to Illuſions, through the falſe Principles every one eſtabliſhes to himſelf in the exerciſe of Piety; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of conceitedneſs, and oftneſt out of weakneſs and ignorance. But after all, there is none of them more ſubject to this then Charity. For as this Vertue has much luſtre, 'tis pretended to upon very many
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48587:39"/>occaſions; chiefly when we think to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and dazle Men, as is uſual enough: And it is not to be wonder'd at if the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of diſſimulation, creeps into the exerciſe of this Vertue, which is the moſt pure and ſincere of all others; ſince the corruption of this Age has ſo powerfully authoriſed all Artifices and Diſguiſes: In effect Self-love, which always ſeeks its own intereſt by ſo many windings about, cannot better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it ſelf then under the veil of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. It is through this Artifice it ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſticks to the Duties of Good-man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to excuſe it ſelf from eſſential Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; It ſeeks conſpicuous Charities to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void obſcure ones; 'Tis zealous where there ſhould be no zeal, and remiſs where there ſhould be. Thus the falſly Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is uneaſie to his own Domeſticks whilſt he is civil and officious to Strangers; he grounds a tranquility and ſatisfaction on the ſtate of his own pretended perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and is only froward and diſquieted at others perfections; he is perpetually praiſing Chriſtianity, and quits nothing of his own Rights; He gives Alms, and pays not his Debts; He maliciouſly praiſes falſe Vertues, to take occaſion to authorize real Vices; He juſtifies his own ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, only by cenſuring that of others;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48587:39"/>and ſcattering Flowers over all he would poiſon, he wounds the Reputation of every one, under the deceitful veil of charitable and reſpectful Words. But to diſcover methodically all the Illuſions, wherewith the Spirit of Charity is ſo often perverted, I reduce them to certain Heads, which are as it were their Sources.</p>
               <p>Natural Affection is the Firſt, and withal the moſt ordinary Illuſion which creeps into the Spirit of Charity: One loves his Neighbour 'tis true, but 'tis only for the good qualities which render him amiable; one looks on him, but on the moſt agreeable ſide, and where he is moſt pleaſing: It is the wit, quality, humour and diſpoſition one conſiders; and the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer one is to all theſe Conſiderations of Fleſh and Bloud, the more inſenſible he is to all thoſe of Vertue and Grace. One be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves 'tis loving his Neighbour as he ought, and living charitably with him, to ſpeak nothing vexatious to any one, to be very regardful and wary of every ones In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in particular; to do very general Civilities to all the World by outward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of Friendſhip, which all in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality ſignifie nothing: This is to prophane the ſacred Name of Charity, to give it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to actions which are often the motions of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48587:40"/>a deprav'd Inclination, and the effects of a habit meerly to follow ones Humour. So that to give Alms out of a natural pity, to be officious and obliging for humane reſpects to love his Friends, his Relations, and Family, becauſe good Breeding en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns to live well with all the World; this is but the Charity of a Pagan. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans love thoſe that love them, conſider thoſe that conſider them, and carry it fair with thoſe that do ſo with them. 'Tis, if you will, Civility, Good-manners, Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Complacence, Policy, and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but it is not Charity at all; It is to have too low a conceit of ſo great a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to give ſo holy a Name to that which is but humane and natural. Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity knows not the meaning of all theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, and theſe unjuſt preferrings of one before another, which the prudence of the Fleſh makes: becauſe a Chriſtian equally conſiders <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in all his Brethren, whom he never looks on with an eye purely humane; Faith teaches him that this ignorant Man he inſtructs, this miſerable Wretch he ſuccours, this poor Man to whom he gives Bread, is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is in the Perſon of the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, as a Prince is in the Perſon of his Ambaſſador. So that the more one finds
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48587:40"/>himſelf naturally inclin'd to Compaſſion, the more he ought to ſtand upon his guard not to practiſe Charity ſo much out of humanity: for as the Apoſtle ſays, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes himſelf to reap only a carnal har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, when he do's not ſow in purity of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; And it is but a miſtaken Chriſtianity that is founded upon the Principles of ſo humane and worldly a Charity.</p>
               <p>The Second Illuſion is of Pride, which, by a ſecret preſumption, and upon the foundation of a very frivolous merit, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces all the perfection of Man in a vain Charity. It is upon this ground the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee in the Goſpel ſet himſelf above others, whoſe carriage he reprehended; becauſe he gave great Alms. And although this Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion may not be common, yet many Chriſtians are found ſubject to it; and who upon the Maxims of a deprav'd Morality give liberally their Goods to the Poor; without forſaking the ſpirit of Injuſtice by which they poſſeſs them; Their hands are open to Mercy, and their hearts ſhut to Equity; They are Envious, Detractors, and Calumniators, upon that miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Principle, That Charity blots out all iniquities, and that it is ſufficient to be a good Man to be compaſſionate of the miſeries of our Neighbour. They adorn
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48587:41"/>the out-ſide with works of ſuperficial Charity, and leave all diſorder and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption within: And what elſe is this, ſays St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> but to give ones Goods to his Neighbour and his Soul up to Sin; <hi>To ſacrifice his Riches to God, and himſelf to the Devil?</hi> They even carry this Illuſion much farther. For there are of thoſe falſly charitable Perſons whoſe Soul is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, that to do theſe Works of Mercy which are proper to blot out their Sins, they commit new ones to have wherewithal to do Works of Mercy. They offer to God, what they have taken from Men; and frame to themſelves an extravagant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to give in Charity what by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they have forc'd from others. How great a Fallacy, to believe that the bitter and envenom'd root of Injuſtice, is able to produce the ſweet and lovely fruit of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity! for <hi>He,</hi> ſays the Scripture, <hi>that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers ſacrifice of poor mens ſubſtance, is as he that ſacrificeth the ſon in the preſence of his father.</hi> We muſt imitate <hi>Zacheus,</hi> to practiſe Charity as me ought: He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by reſtoring what he had taken, to give the remainder to the Poor. In this manner Chriſtian Charity is neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous nor unjuſt; and ſhe is always without Violence, for ſhe is never without humility.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:48587:41"/>
               <p>The Third Illuſion is Covetouſneſs, which out of a narrowneſs of heart and miſerableneſs ſeeks falſe reaſons, of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Children, Parcimony and good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, to authorize this falſe Prudence in Men not to diſpoſſeſs themſelves of their Goods by giving them to the Poor. But it is a diſtruſt fit for Pagans to fear falling into want by giving, in the Perſon of the Needy, to a God whoſe riches are inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible: for <hi>He that ſhall give to the poor ſhall never want the goods of the earth:</hi> as holy Scripture ſays. Alms, ſays S. <hi>Paul,</hi> is a Seed whence cannot be reap'd but a very great Harveſt. And as the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man when he ſows much, reaps much; So the faithful ſhall reap a plentiful Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt when they have given great Alms. The fulneſs of the Charity of a Chriſtian ſhall make the fulneſs of his Recompence. But theſe are Truths the avaritious Man do's not comprehend, through the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fixedneſs he has to the Goods of this World: He hoards up his Bonds and Money carefully in the bottom of his Cheſts, whilſt he perſwades others to be Charitable: He ſtrains for poor Pretenees for his not giving when he is ask'd: He remits to his Council all Propoſitions made him for Charity, to authorize his Avarice,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48587:42"/>and refuſe more methodically what he is unwilling to grant: He do's all he can to excuſe his giving, and never gives but in hopes of receiving: His Charity is a meer Traffick: He ſo ſtrongly blinds himſelf even in his preſumption, that he makes a falſe vertue of his conduct: He ſays with a haughty and diſdainful ayre, I have no Goods of another bodies, nay I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire any; I make uſe of what God has given me, becauſe he has only beſtow'd it on me for my uſe. This was heretofore the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that unhappy rich Man, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd himſelf nothing that he liked. His Expence was magnificent at his Table, in his Train, in his Cloaths, and his whole Family bore the marks of his Vanity and Pride: whilſt <hi>Lazarus</hi> dy'd with hunger at his Dore. 'Tis likewiſe the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Illuſion of Great Men, that their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs makes them covetous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of the miſeries of the afflicted. They waſte their Eſtates profuſely in cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Expences, and refuſe a poor Man a bit of Bread; So that out of a mean Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs they extravagantly ſquander away thoſe Goods wherewith God had intruſted them to diſtribute. Hereunto may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the miſtake of thoſe mercileſs People, who give no Alms but with an ill will and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48587:42"/>grumbling: It is not to the Poor they give, it is to their importunities, and to the vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they feel in being preſſed by them. Hence they follow their own humour; not practiſe Charity. 'Tis fruitleſly they give, becauſe they give without any fellow-feeling: So as they experience not the ſweetneſs which joys his heart that practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Charity; but when one is fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Poor repreſent the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he is always touch'd with their miſeries, and never ſhock'd with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing importun'd.</p>
               <p>The Fourth is a deceitful Tenderneſs, perpetually ſubject to make it ones own caſe. This Illuſion is common to certain Perſons too ſenſible of Nature, who have no tenderneſs to their Neighbour but out of tenderneſs to themſelves: And duly examining the ground of their pity, they are not compaſſionate of others miſeries but out of a weakneſs of mind which makes them fear the like. They do not commonly reguard their Neighbour but by the reſemblance to themſelves. They are not ſenſible of others Misfortunes, but through the apprehenſion they have of the condition of their own Nature, expos'd to ſo many accidents and miſeries. They perceive not this altogether as it is: It is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48587:43"/>an almoſt imperceptible Illuſion of Self-love; and though it ſeldom happens, it ſuffices that it may happen, to oblige a Chriſtian to make ſome reflection on it, and to diſintangle himſelf from thoſe ſo humane and ſelf-intereſted tenderneſſes. Chriſtian Charity is of too pure a nature to ſuffer them; And 'tis not to be ſincerely and Chriſtian-like Charitable to be ſo only out of humour and a meer natural motive.</p>
               <p>The Fifth is a falſe Zeal of Religion and Piety, out of which they pretend to reprehend the good actions of others, and find ſomething to ſay againſt all: like the Phariſees of whom St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaks; who were ſcandaliz'd at <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> curing a ſick Man preſented to him, becauſe 'twas on a Feſtival Day; And like that Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Diſciple who was troubled at the Piety of that holy Woman who pour'd out moſt precious Ointment on our Saviours Feet, pretending it might have been ſold for the relief of the Poor. This likewiſe is a moſt ordinary Illuſion of a falſe Devotion, which often fixes it ſelf to exterior Ceremonies, and neglects the moſt eſſential Duties of Charity; and on certain occaſions tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the moſt ſacred Laws, to ſuſtain indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly pretended Formalities. It is by this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48587:43"/>Spirit Men preſcribe to others what they do not obſerve themſelves; that they make continual reflections on their Neighbours conduct, and mind not their own; that they are clear-ſighted to the leaſt defects of others, and perceive not their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders; that they take upon them to give advice to all the World, and ſmother the dictates of their own Conſcience. 'Tis an adheſion to their own ſence, and a miſtaken Zeal which often reigns amongſt the Churchmen themſelves; They men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nothing but their Power, they talk of nothing but their Character, and alledge nothing but their Authority; They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'twere diſhonouring their Function to accommodate themſelves charitably to the weakneſs of thoſe whom God has put under their Charge, and that 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs to be condeſcending: Thus they are all fire to make their Ordinances be obſerv'd, but cool and indifferent for thoſe of the Goſpel. They know all the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that lead to deſtruction, but do not ſo much as know thoſe that lead to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and under pretence to eſtabliſh the Diſcipline of the ancient Canons, they abandon oftentimes the true Spirit of the Church, which is a Conduct of ſweetneſs and condeſcendency. Behold in general the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48587:44"/>Spirit of falſe Zeal which ſupports it ſelf ordinarily by the bare appearance of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But it is always eaſie to diſtinguiſh the true from the falſe: For true Vertue is edified with every thing, and the falſe takes ſcandal at all: and as there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation that do's not appear pure to the one; ſo there is no carriage, let it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo irreproachable, but appears de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective to the other.</p>
               <p>The Sixth is Envy, which cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold without trouble the advantage of on's Neighbour; for ſhe finds her humiliation in the ſucceſs and proſperity of others. And if ſometimes the Envious has ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent moderation, not to pretend by indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect means to the good of his Brother: yet has he not ſo much as to hear without emotion the noiſe his Reputation makes in the world; He endures his Neighbours good Fortune, but cannot bear the repute of it. This poiſon, as groſs as it is, ſlips ſometimes into the Soul of ſuch as profeſs Vertue. There are good People, and of a very holy Converſation, who like the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in the Goſpel, after having been faithful to their Miniſtry, in the exerciſe of Charity, permit themſelves to be poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with Jealouſie: they cannot endure New-comers ſhould ſhare the publick
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48587:44"/>Eſteem with them. This is a weakneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a Miniſter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in following ſo miſerable a Conduct, <hi>They often conſummate with the fleſh,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>what they began with the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Seventh is the Wiſdom and Spirit of the World. It is by this Spirit ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to that of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that People make profeſſion of Charity, to get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Perſons of Conſideration; and deal in good Works, that they may have occaſion to deal with thoſe who do them: By this means they inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into their Eſteems, gain Credit, make Friends, and do their own Buſineſs by acting for other Folks. The ſmall Alms which get them admittance into this Society of Charity, help ſometimes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs their ſecret deſigns of making their Fortunes. This may ſerve, if for nothing elſe, at leaſt to conceal their Humour, and diſguiſe their Character towards compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Ends: By this means they give themſelves out for what they are not, and may paſs for good Men without being concern'd whether they are ſo or no; This is all their ſtudy, and they guide all their Actions by the Maxims of this Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical Charity, which is only animated by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48587:45"/>the Spirit of the World and Wiſdom of the Fleſh. 'Tis by the Maxims of this falſe Charity and a chimerical Zeal, that under pretext of doing more good they aſpire to Places they have not, and omit the good they could do in the Place they are in. Nay they artificially endeavour their own Advancement in a more effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious way, while they ſeem to relie on Providence; and quietly expect from God what in reality they mean to get only by the ſecret Intrigues of Men. Thus they change the Principles of Chriſtianity, into thoſe of carnal Morality. If in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance they have any moderation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Neighbours, it is only the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to act a conceal'd Vanity wherewith ſecretly they ſatisfie themſelves: If they pardon an Injury, it is to expect a better opportunity of Revenge: If they do good, it is out of hopes of a Return. All is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the Maxims of this humane Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſo oppoſite to the Wiſdom of the Goſpel. And as by theſe ways (which tend to God only in appearance) they go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from him; they wilfully blind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Errors, to the end not to ſee the diſproportion between what they do, and what they ought to do.</p>
               <p>The Eighth is Indiſcretion. This breaks
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48587:45"/>the order in which Charity that ought to be laudable and vertuous ſhould be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and plays all thoſe irregular Tricks which put this Vertue out of frame. It is by this Illuſion that after publick Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they make Reparations of Honor more to be fear'd then the Detractions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and which for the moſt part ſerve but to open again the Wound they pretend to cloſe. Through this 'tis Men would ſuccour others when they are no longer in a Condition to be aſſiſted: like the rich Glutton, who puts on the Charitable after his death for the ſalvation of his Brethren, whom he would have advertis'd of their licentiouſneſs; though he had never pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd Charity during his life. It is through this perverſion of Reaſon ſome give Alms, and pay not their Debts; viſit Priſons, and mind not their domeſtick Affairs; by their Wills leave the moſt Chriſtian-like Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in the World at their Deaths, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Peace and Union of their Family; refuſe one truly Poor wherewith to draw him out of miſery, and without diſcretion give a Wanderer and a Vagabond where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to maintain them in their idleneſs. They run about the World to Convert People, without thinking to Convert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and ſometimes loſe themſelves in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48587:46"/>ſeeking too earneſtly after thoſe that have ſtray'd. To this Illuſion may be reduced the miſtaken Conduct of thoſe Directors, who by indiſcreet Rigors pervert the Ways of God in driving ſometimes Sinners from their Confeſſionary Seats, whom his Grace brings thither; and diſheartning the weak, for want of capacity and advice to manage them in their weakneſs. I ſay nothing of the Indiſcretion of thoſe Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who believe themſelves Charitable becauſe they do not ſteal their Neighbours Goods, while they rob them of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor by their Calumnies: They care not for folks Purſes, but flie at the Reputation of all the World; there's no ſaving on's ſelf from their Tongues: they examine not a jot all that is ſaid, to have the more right to believe every thing; and there's none talk'd of diſadvantageouſly, but they are preſently perſwaded all that's ſaid is true. In fine, it is this Spirit of Indiſcretion that breaks all the ordinary meaſures of Charity, and takes from it that diſcernment of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, without which this Vertue becomes it ſelf inconſiderable: For ſometimes it accuſes where it ought to excuſe; and on other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions praiſes where it ought to reprehend: being thus often ſubject to miſtake through Precipitation, and the lightneſs of Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:48587:46"/>
               <p>The Ninth is the Spirit of Severity: for Severity narrows the Heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives it of that extent of Soul which is the chief character of Charity. 'Tis from this Principle ſome believe they ought not to indulge any, becauſe they pardon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nothing; and think they have a right to be ſevere to others, becauſe they are ſo to themſelves. S. <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Siena</hi> avows ſhe was ſubject to this fault in her firſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, out of a falſe Vertue; and the moſt vertuous can hardly guard themſelves from this weakneſs: for 'tis natural for a Man to judge of his Neighbour, when he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more perfect then him. The care one has to live irreprochably in the World, gives a pretence of title to reproch every thing in others: and one eaſily perſwades himſelf he owes none that lenity and indulgence which he refuſes to himſelf. If he ſpeaks 'tis roughly, if he gives his advice 'tis ſeverely, if he reprehends 'tis with impatience and rage. 'Tis ever a bitter zeal and moroſe ayre, which is ſeldom other then the effect of a dark and melancholy humour; ſcarce ever the ſpirit of Charity: In which reſpect this Conduct is but a falſe Severity; for Chriſtian Severity is rigid only to its ſelf, and indulgent to others. This too was the fault of the Phariſee, who blam'd all the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48587:47"/>reſt of Mankind, becauſe, Faſting 'twice a week, he believ'd himſelf better then them all. Thus 'tis that Men are ſevere to their Neighbour when they are ſo to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they ſpare none becauſe they favour not themſelves, and that they ſpeak ill of all the World becauſe they have a ſeverer Morality then others. And thus Severity becomes a meer Deluſion, if found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on any other Principle then Charity. Let us place our Glory then rather in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Charity, then in the auſterity of our Morals. For, <hi>Should we live only on Aſhes,</hi> ſays S. Chryſoſtom, <hi>if we have not indulgence, and love for our Neighbour, this auſterity would avail us nothing:</hi> And generally Pride, which is the ordinary effect of this Spirit of Severity, is ſo great an obſtacle to Charity, that men ought to ſtand ſo much the more on their guard as they find themſelves inclinable to Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Vertue her ſelf ought to redouble her Diſtruſts amidſt the Applauſes ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives; for ſhe becomes a ſnare as ſoon as ſhe ceaſes to be pure. There is nothing ſo dangerous as Diſorder back'd with a falſe Zeal, as an adheſion to Error hid under the veil of an exemplar Life, and as ſtrict Morality with a licentious Belief. But if Severity be oppoſite to Charity
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48587:47"/>when not founded on Mildneſs; Mildneſs is no leſs contrary on ſeveral occaſions, when not ſupported by Severity: For it runs into a ſlackning of Order either by a ſoft Indulgence, or by a timorous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. In effect, Clemency is pernicious where there needs Rigor, and Silence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a fault when one ſhould Speak. He prevaricates that holds his Tongue in thoſe occaſions where Counſels and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs are abſolutely neceſſary. Judgment and Knowledge, which ought to be the two inſeparable companions of Charity, will find a middle path between theſe two Extreams, to the edification of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the only Mark that Charity ſhould aim at.</p>
               <p>The Tenth is Hypocriſie. This is the Illuſion of the Phariſees in the Goſpel, who affect being ſcrupulous about Trifles, and at the bottom have no principle of Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Honeſty. They humble their Souls before God by big-look'd Pennances; and harden their Hearts to the complaints of the Afflicted and ſighs of the Poor: They cover their Violences and Injuſtice with the veil of Devotion and Piety. This is the Diſorder that reigns moſt in this Age, where Diſguiſe ſits upon the very Altar: Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is ſcarce any longer practis'd but to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48587:48"/>get Reputation; Men only ſeek to impoſe: becauſe they mean but to dazle: They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that Charity which is of obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and commanded, to practiſe that which is only councell'd; They reſpect the mighty, to inſult over the weak; They have ſhameful Condeſcendencies for Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, and nothing but Rigour and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs for the Mean; They propoſe to themſelves imaginary Deſigns of good Works impoſſible to be effected, and leave thoſe that be very eaſie and neceſſary. But this Hypocriſie may be diſcerned better if taken a pieces: This perſon ſo exteriourly moderate, and who through an artificial carriage has the repute of being ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, is a Fury at home; In publick he's Charitable, and a Backbiter in private; In Company he ſpeaks well of every one, but ſpares none at his ſecret Cabals; He's affable to thoſe he eſteems, but rude to thoſe he diſreguards; His Devotions are as regular as can be, and he would paſs for a Saint, if he were not ſo revengeful and ſo dextrous to ſatisfie his Reſentments where he has any Conteſts; None ever offends him without ſmarting for it; for he never forgives: So that by this his affected Moderation his Life is a continual Impoſture. There are a thouſand other
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48587:48"/>Diſguiſes of Charity which may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to this, and which are ſo much the more odious in the ſight of God, as being done under the pretext of Piety. Vice is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways criminal; but the moſt criminal of all is that which is done under the Coulor and Veil of Vertue: for Men leſs ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be corrupted by a bare-fac'd Vice, then a maſqued Vertue. After all, 'tis in vain to diſguiſe on's ſelf: nothing can be hid from his ſight that ſearches hearts and penetrates to the very bottom of them.</p>
               <p>The Eleventh is a Spirit of Empire and Dominion. They are willing to be in at all good Works, provided they may Rule, Direct and Manage: They make one in all Deſigns and Enterprizes of Charity, out of the ſweetneſs they feel in Governing things with ſome Authority; and the pleaſure there is to exerciſe that petty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire which expreſſes its ſelf in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their Neighbours wants, and the diſtribution of aſſiſtance given them. They meet punctually at Aſſemblies, as ſo many favourable occaſions of ſhewing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and give their wealth to new Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations to Reign in them. 'Tis out of this ſame Spirit that they thruſt themſelves with ſuch zeal into all manner of Affairs; that they are ſo earneſt to render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48587:49"/>neceſſary in them; that they love Negotiating to find out a Temperament in Accommodations and Arbitrations; that they charitably concern themſelves in every thing; that they have a Wit fertile enough in Expedients to be of Councel for all the World; and that they give ſo liberal advice upon the Conduct of all Mankind. For this is the Character of the Devotion of theſe Times; it will be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and Govern all. 'Tis through this ſame Spirit that Men have no value but for the good Works they do themſelves; That they will not abet any good unleſs themſelves do it; and that there are ſome who cannot endure either Religion ſhould be defended or Vertue protected, but after their way, their lights, and their methods: They condemn all elſe be it never ſo good; They have not the leaſt concern for it, becauſe they have no ſhare in it. They ſet up for Directors without any Vocation or Character: for Direction now adays, as it is ordered, is very comfortable to thoſe that Direct; becauſe they ſpeak with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and find Submiſſion every where. In ſhort, this Spirit of Command is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo much the Spirit of this Age, that it is crept in among Perſons conſecrated to the Altars; who take on them in all the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48587:49"/>Functions of their Miniſtry a certain ayre of Independence, whilſt they hold the reſt of the World in Subjection. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who had in his hands all the Authority of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is an excellent Pattern for Chriſtian Paſtors: for he never made uſe of all his great Power to deſtroy, but only to edifie. In effect this abſolute Authority is a Conduct too diſmal and fierce for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; ſerving only to make the Yoke of Obedience more burthenſom, unleſs tempered with Love and Charity. True Paſtors do themſelves more honor in being the Fathers of Souls, then their Lords and Maſters; and in loving to Rule their Flocks with ſweetneſs and tenderneſs, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then with haughtineſs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. <hi>You muſt,</hi> ſays S. Bernard, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand with humility to Command like a Chriſtian;</hi> And there's nothing prepares the Hearts of Subjects to Submiſſion like the Charity of thoſe they obey.</p>
               <p>The Twelfth Illuſion is Scandal and Ill-Example. 'Tis through this Illuſion Men live diſorderly whilſt they flatter themſelves with fair appearances of a kind of natural Equity, which they would have a horror to tranſgreſs: They have at bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom a zeal for Juſtice, and have none for modeſty: They are tender of a Stranger's
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48587:50"/>Intereſt, and ſacrifice the Innocence of a Domeſtick, of whom they ſerve themſelves in the ſecret practices of their Paſſion: They are touch'd with the Misfortunes of one unknown whom they ſee oppreſſed, and ruine the Conſcience of a Friend whom they cauſe to engage in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. You are not Violent, you are not Unjuſt, you hate Oppreſſion, Cruelty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſes you; in brief you wrong no body: And you employ your Wives in ſhameful Concerns and vicious Intrigues. You are nice even to ſcruple, in point of Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and have all the affectations of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, to ſeduce Youth that puts it ſelf into your Hands. How many Diſorders have you cauſed by your Scandals, you that have ſo much averſion for Injuſtice? for your Example is a Poiſon that kills him who ſees it. But what is become of the Modeſty of Chriſtian Ladies in an Age, where nothing is talk'd of but Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Devotion? Was there ever ſeen ſo great a licentiouſneſs in Manners as now adays? Women, beſides the indecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and immodeſty of their Dreſs, are even come to think it a greater ayre of Quality to dreſs themſelves publickly and before all the World: that is to ſay, to expoſe themſelves, by a ſcandalous Mode, to thoſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48587:50"/>adulterous Eyes whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaks; and to Preſent in the Golden Veſſel, like the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the mortal Draught to thoſe that ſee them. Scandal is ſo dreadful a ſpring of Corruption, and ſo pernicious a poiſon to Innocence; that one cannot have Faith and read, without Trembling, the terrible Menaces of the Son of God to thoſe ſcandalous Perſons who poiſon the Souls of thoſe with whom they converſe. Our Lord ſeems to have forbidden in the Goſpel nothing ſo ſtrictly as this: <hi>Cut,</hi> ſays he, <hi>cut off, pluck out even your very eyes, if your eyes ſcandalize you.</hi> I ſay nothing of thoſe fond fooliſh Mothers, who by their Indulgency and Vanity ruine the Innocency of their young Daughters, in expoſing them to Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and dangerous Companies, under pretence of ſhewing and teaching them the World: I ſpeak not of thoſe enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom'd Tongues that tear in pieces the Honor of their Neighbour, in moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and reſpectful Language, and ſow Diſſention wherever they come. I only ſay that a Chriſtian cannot without trembling make reflection on thoſe dreadful words of the Son of God, <hi>Wo to him by whom ſcandal cometh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Thirteenth is the Spirit of Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48587:51"/>and Partiality, principally in matters of Religion: and this is the moſt dangerous of all Illuſions. 'Tis out of this Spirit that Men make uſe of the holy Name of <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> to heighten their Averſions, and render their Enmities irreconcileable. By this they cenſure the Conduct of others to authorize their own; They deſtroy ſettled Reputation to give themſelves more Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; They frame to themſelves a <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera</hi> of Religion, to ſeek a more ſpecious pretext for their Headſtrongneſs, and they give their Paſſion the name of Zeal and Charity. Such was the Illuſion of that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady <hi>Lucilla,</hi> mention'd by S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine;</hi> ſhe was Rich, Devout, and of Quality: and ſhe it was who, ſuffering her ſelf to be dazled with Viſions of her own Zeal, kindled, by the profuſion of her Alms and great Repute, the firſt ſparks of that fire, wherewith the Hereſie of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> laid waſte the Church of <hi>Africa,</hi> and afterwards ſpread it ſelf over <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> Such likewiſe was the Extravagancy of that rich Merchant of <hi>Lyons</hi> call'd <hi>Valdo,</hi> who upon a fancy of Reformation fooliſhly diſtributed all his Wealth to the Poor; whence ſprung that curſed Sect of the <hi>Valdenſes,</hi> which ſince has been the ſource of other Hereſies that have infected
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48587:51"/>
                  <hi>France.</hi> Such in fine was the Illuſion of the <hi>Sacramentarians</hi> of the laſt Age, who taking upon them to be Reformers, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied a new Morality to draw peoples Eyes upon their Party, and more ſignalize their Conduct. They ſpoke of nothing but Sweetneſs, Chriſtian Integrity, the New Teſtament and the Goſpel. <hi>My Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and my Siſters</hi> was the common Language of theſe Preachers when they ſpoke to the People. In fine, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Reformation all places eccho'd with the fair and ſpecious Name of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Union: whilſt they cut the Throats of Prieſts, broke down the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, writ moſt invective Libels againſt the Divines of the <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Church, and rendred all Morals ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to eſtabliſh that which they vented. The Vices of thoſe that declar'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves favourers of that Party were Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; The Vertues of thoſe that favour'd them not were accounted Vices: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of Vertue and Honeſty wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on their breath, and none had any Chriſtianity, if you'l believe them, but in as much as they embrac'd their Judgments, and were their Friends. All this Conduct was defective, becauſe grounded on a falſe Principle; And theſe appearances of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48587:52"/>whereof they boaſted, were but a pure piece of Policy, and a ſecret Artifice to authorize their Party, and make their Error ſpread the better.</p>
               <p>The Fourteenth is a hidden Vanity that finds its way into almoſt all Works of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: 'Tis ſo natural to Man to ſeek him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all things, even the moſt holy, that he is ſo much the more ſubject to this weakneſs, as he is exempt from all the reſt. It pleaſes ſome to Teach, Inſtruct and Direct, becauſe thereby they get Credit. They love Charities that make a ſhew, becauſe they would be particularly taken notice of. They find wants at their Doors, and regard them not; and ſend their Alms to the end of the World, becauſe that makes a greater noiſe. They pardon an Offence with all the Ceremonies of ſatisfaction in form, to raiſe a Trophy of their Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They exerciſe, out of a falſe generoſity, Liberalities diſproportionable to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and fail their Brother in his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. 'Tis often nothing but Vanity that makes thoſe famous Wills wherein Friends are ſo well conſider'd: they merit much by it in the eyes of the World, but nothing in the ſight of God: It conduces much to the reputation of him that dies, and avails nothing to the Expiation of his ſins, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48587:52"/>his Juſtification. At his death, he has given his Goods to his beſt Friends; It looks very handſom, but it is very Pagan-like; herein he conſiders Friendſhip, and regards not Charity. It is not for the love of God that this Lady is Charitable, 'tis only for the love of her ſelf; 'Tis out of this Spirit that ſhe is in at all good Works: Being vain, ſhe is not diſpleas'd at being thank'd for the good ſhe do's; for ſhe do's it only for that end. Her Charity being but a pretext to her Vanity, ſhe endeavours much more to appear Charitable, then to be ſo in effect; but wo to them who give Alms to be ſeen, and ſo gain the applauſe of Men: <hi>For</hi> (ſays the Goſpel) <hi>they have already receiv'd their reward.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though an Alms given on this account is profitable to the Receiver, yet is it wholly unprofitable to the Giver: This infectious ayre of Vanity that mixes with it, is in it ſelf alone ſufficient to ſpoil the fruit. Alms, to be Chriſtian, ought to be humble; and done in private, to be profitable to the Doer, <hi>That our heavenly Father,</hi> ſaith S. Matthew, <hi>who ſees in ſecret, may give him his recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</hi> What in this place the Goſpel ſpeaks of Alms, ought to be underſtood of all Works of Charity; which a Chriſtian ought to do with a pure and ſincere inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48587:53"/>deſiring God only for witneſs: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the worm of Vanity deſtroys his Works, and renders them unprofitable in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>The Fifteenth is a diſorderly addicted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Devotions; which gives to God what is due to our Neighbour. Some neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their Families to be more aſſiduous at the foot of the Altar; They wave their Employments to be doing Kindneſſes; They love retiredneſs, when their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion obliges them to appear in publick; They are ſilent out of a falſe modeſty. when they ſhould ſpeak; They meditate when they ſhould act; They are in Office, and live like private Perſons; They would have peace with God without caring to have it with Men. This Paſtor in his Flock, This Superior in his Houſe, are Mild, Peaceable, and Charitable; but they ſuffer themſelves to be govern'd by furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirits, whoſe Paſſions they eſpouſe: and allgo's topſie-turvie ſometimes by their Authority, whilſt they are at the feet of their Crucifix to ſatisfie the guſt of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſome ſentiment of Piety, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love of Eaſe gives them unſeaſonably. They deceive themſelves, if they believe they are innocent of the Violences done in their Name; for 'tis only their Name that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:48587:53"/>authorizes them. This is to be but the vain Image of a Paſtor, ſays the Prophet; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 'tis to be but Charitable in <hi>Idea,</hi> to have the heart to abandon his Flock, to leave the Conduct of it to Paſtors foiſted in, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt with another the Salvation of thoſe, for whom himſelf in perſon is reſponſible to God. A watchful Superior ought to be like a wiſe Pilot, who has always his Hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rudder: every thing alarms him by reaſon of the concern he takes in the ſafety of thoſe he conducts. And as they are not in Office but to watch over thoſe they Govern; ſo all the Vertues, all the Graces, and all the moſt holy Actions of Superiors are deceitful, when they ſeek more their ſatisfaction in Devotion then the peace of thoſe they Govern.</p>
               <p>The Sixteenth is Self-love. This Love includes in it ſelf the intereſt of all other Paſſions, and almoſt the univerſal ſpring of all other Illuſions. 'Tis through this Principle of Self-love that Men ſometimes are not in at Practices of Charity, but to manage more dextrouſly their own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: They find hereby their Affairs go much the better; and that ſometimes ſerves to ſuſtain their Rights more boldly, and even more creditably. We ſee in effect Perſons of Quality Charitable, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48587:54"/>underſtand Chriſtianity, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct others to practice it, and diſtribute in their Mannors well-order'd Alms to the Poor of the County; but they will not quit any thing of their Intereſts: 'Tis they advance them ſometimes even beyond the bounds of Equity. Fain they would be well at Court with every one: but the <hi>Chimera</hi> of their Birth and Quality is ſo ſtrong in their Head, that they become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable to all the Nobility of their own County; and are ſo jealous of their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Rights, that they forget all the care they ought to have of Charity and Edification. This Prelate ſo ſet upon his Duty, is inflexible when the Functions of his Miniſtry are in queſtion: He talks of nothing now but his Power; his great zeal is to exerciſe his Power in Eccleſiaſtical Judgments according to the rigor of the Canons, and to hold up even unto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of Edification, the intereſt of his Dignity. But after all, the matter well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, ways there are more mild and Chriſtian-like to defend his Rights, then thoſe of Haughtineſs and Authority: and ordinarily he makes uſe of his Authority too much, only to ſupply his want of merit and conceal his weakneſs. This Lady has an admirable indifference for all things,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48587:54"/>but is ſo wedded to her own Fancy, that ſhe paſſionately defends all her Sentiments. She is the moſt moderate Perſon in the World; but her Moderation leaves her as ſoon as ſhe finds her Intereſt in any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair mixt with thoſe of others. She receives kindly every one except her Creditors: She is humble and modeſt, but has ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Niceties in point of Reputation. 'Tis this Self-love which is ſo exact to obſerve Civility in Works of Charity: 'Twould ſhock her ſhould ſhe not pay her Devoirs to a ſick Relation, though little eſteem'd; or not to be one at a good Work with her beſt Friends, leaſt ſhe ſhould appear ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; nor to give to a Box-carrier ſhe eſteems and values. In fine, theſe are but low and ſelf-ended Regards: men act out of meer humane and worldly Conſiderations; And Chriſtian Charity is rarely practis'd in its purity.</p>
               <p>There is an infinity of other Illuſions I do not mention, which a little attention to our ſelves will make us reflection: As to diſſemble the Truth, where Charity ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges to declare it, out of a too humane fear of ſcandal or ſome other inconvenience; To forbear giving Alms, to avoid the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity one is ſubject to in giving them; To ſcandalize ones Neighbour out of too great
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48587:55"/>deſire to edifie him; To wound Charity under pretext to practiſe it; To give poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd praiſes to what one would diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend; To invent ſubtle Detractions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd with great Commendations, to deſtroy more methodically thoſe one would ruine; To mend with artificial Fetches what one would mar; To comfort a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Perſon, and blaſt the Credit of one that is happy; To impoſe a Yoke on our Neighbour which he cannot bear; To be ruling others, and to be ones ſelf irregular; To ſeek after Infidels to convert them, and not to love our Brethren; To ſee evil and not to examine it; To condemn without being inform'd; To uſe for ones peculiar Intereſt the Talents one has to be uſeful to his Neighbour; To draw to ones ſelf, by the Miniſtry of the Word of God, the Eſteem of thoſe one ought to draw to God himſelf only; To diſſipate ones ſelf, by inſtructing them; To impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh ones ſelf by enriching them with ones Lights; To be too fond of the ſucceſs, and purſue it with more inquietude then one ought in the exerciſe of Charity; In fine, the very perfecteſt acts of Charity are but meer Illuſions, when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the perfection of that State where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto God has call'd one. As for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48587:55"/>If a <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> who ought to lead a ſolitary life, would become a Miſſioner; or if a <hi>Carmelite</hi> would from his Grate convert the World by the Intrigues of his Direction: for both the one and the other would act therein contrary to their Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But 'tis obſervable that if Charity be ſubject to all theſe Illuſions, in reſpect of its Principle; yet 'tis not ſubject to any in reſpect of its object: for when the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of it is pure, 'tis always <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> one aſſiſts in the Poor and the Afflicted, altho it be an Impoſture that is aſſiſted; becauſe 'tis <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> alone one has in view when he acts like a Chriſtian. After all, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining thorowly theſe divers ſorts of Illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, one will find they are all but the real diſguiſes of Self-love, which is the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt enemy of Charity.</p>
               <p>But 'tis to be fear'd leſt, endeavouring to refine Charity overmuch by a too ſtrict obſervation of theſe Illuſions, the greateſt part whereof ſeldom happen, the exerciſe of this Vertue be rendred ſo difficult that its practice be wholly ruin'd: For 'tis eaſily ſaid Man is expos'd to ſo many occaſions of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to ſo many Imperfections through the weakneſs of his Condition, that 'tis to render the uſe of Charity impoſſible to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend he muſt practiſe it ſo purely. It ſeems
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48587:56"/>even that God ſerves himſelf of the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Man, that the Poor may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; yet he would not be ſo, if it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on ſo pure a practice of this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. I affirm the Poor are frequently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, through the Vanity and other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of thoſe that ſuccour them: for Man commonly acts as Man, that is to ſay, very imperfectly: But is that a reaſon his Eyes ſhould not be open to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to reflect on't? If God makes uſe of our Paſſions as the moſt ordinary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his Deſigns; If the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſprings of his Providence for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of great Events, are moſt commonly ſet on work by the Intrigue of Intereſt or Ambition of Men; And if his Wiſdom is ſo wonderful as to draw from thoſe corrupted and envenom'd Sources the pureſt Draughts of his Glory: 'Tis as much as to ſay, we muſt not dare to ſpeak againſt Paſſions, and advertiſe Man of his weakneſs, becauſe God makes uſe thereof to Govern the World; as he do's of the Vanity of great Men to ſupply the Wants of the mean. For the reſt, I ſhall eſteem my ſelf abundantly recompenced for the pains I have taken to clear ſo home by piecemeal theſe Illuſions, to which Charity is ſubject; if it may ſerve any one to reflect
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48587:56"/>thereon, and to practiſe ſometimes this Vertue with more purity: And I hope God will bleſs the intentions I have had, to endeavour rectifying the uſe of it, by the ſimple and diſintereſted face thereof him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has ſhewn me. But, when Charity ſhall be fully cleared from theſe clouds that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure it, and from all thoſe impure fogs that corrupt it: we muſt think of the means to acquire this Vertue, in rooting out what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is contrary to the purity of its Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Means to acquire Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</head>
               <p>THere is no Rule methodically to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Chriſtian Charity, which is a ſupernatural Habit, and a Gift purely from God. But as a Chriſtian, prevented by Grace, may diſpoſe his Mind to Faith, as ſupernatural as it is, by deſtroying therein obſtinacy, preſumption, and adheſion to Error, and that natural propenſity that leads to Incredulity: So may he after the ſame manner diſpoſe himſelf to attain Charity, if he roots the obſtacles of it out of his heart. For this Vertue finds very great
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48587:57"/>ones in the heart of Man: whereof I will give a touch on the principal; without falling on the ſame Particulars I mention'd in the Illuſions, the moſt part whereof are alſo impediments to Charity.</p>
               <p>The greateſt of all obſtacles to Charity is that Worldly ſpirit, ſo oppoſite to the Spirit of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> That Prudence of the Fleſh, that Pride of the Age, and all that vain Oſtentation which reigns ſo much in the Courts of Great men: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Worldly wiſdom teaches theſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Maxims, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To deſtroy by ſubtle Artifices ones Neighbour's Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; To diſcredit him in the opinion of ſuch as eſteem him; To violate the moſt holy Rights, turn all things topſie-turvy to attain what one pretends to, and to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandize ones ſelf. 'Tis by this ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit young Gentlemen are taught that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge is a Gentleman's Vertue; and that it is a piece of Cowardiſe to pardon. The Hatreds, Envies, Jealouſies, Intrigues of Licentiouſneſs and Ambition, great Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, violent Paſſions, which are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon effects of this Spirit, reigns ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the Great of this World, that they leave not room for the leaſt ſpark of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Therefore the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>He that will become a friend of the world, becomes an enemy of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:48587:57"/>
               <p>There is another Spirit in the World ſtill more oppoſite to this Vertue; the Spirit of Diſguiſe, Impoſture, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, whoſe only end is to miſchief our Neighbour. 'Tis this unhappy Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of the Fleſh, which only ſeeks to eſtabliſh it ſelf by ſhameful and wicked Treacheries, and by all the depraved Maxims of the World, I have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and which render the Life of a Chriſtian a monſtrous Life; that is, full of Paſſions, Animoſities, Knavery and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs. Theſe are the Machines Men make uſe of to perpetuate their Enmities, by everlaſting Wranglings, and to make all Tribunals ring with their Injuſtices and Violences.</p>
               <p>I'le ſay nothing of the Spirit of Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, Contradiction, diverſity of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Opinions in matters of Religion; nor of all thoſe Factious Sidings which at preſent afflict Chriſtianity. The memory of the Diſorders they have cauſed in the laſt Age, is ſtill freſh enough in this to make us comprehend the importance of it: for there is nothing more capable of dividing the hearts of the People, then different Judgments in Religion.</p>
               <p>Being given to Pleaſures, to Delights, to dangerous Divertiſements, to Gaming, to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48587:58"/>Riot, and Delicacy, is alſo a great obſtacle to this Spirit of Charity we are in queſt of. Theſe ſtately Houſes, proud rich Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitures, ſumptuous Tables, new Faſhions in Clothes, which ſhew nothing but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs; Theſe Vanities of worldly La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, this State that environs them, theſe profuſe Expences of voluptuous ſenſual Perſons intoxicated with the Delights of the Age, do ſo forcibly dry up in the hearts of Worldlings this holy Unction of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that there remains not any ſign of it in all thoſe who are plunged in Vanity. For how can a Woman that denies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to her Pleaſure, and loves only her ſelf, be touch'd with any ſentiments of Charity? She ſhuts her Eyes againſt the poverty of the neceſſitous, ſhe will not ſee it, nor ſo much as take notice of it, that ſhe may not ſquander the Fund ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns for her Vanity, by the Aſſiſtance ſhe ſhould be oblig'd to give him that demands it in Gods name: And hence it is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſo often ſhakes with cold, in the Perſon of the Poor at the Gate of the Rich, without being taken notice of; for he is only buſied about himſelf.</p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay of thoſe perpetual Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treds and inveterate Averſions, which Men ſo ſcandalouſly retain? they can neither
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48587:58"/>ſpeak to, nor ſo much as look on one that hath affronted them; and believe their Reſentment juſt, becauſe they have been injur'd. What is more contrary to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſtianity, which cannot ſo much as ſuffer coldneſs or indifferency? They flatter themſelves too, as they frame their Conſciences in their Hatreds and Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; They believe they wiſh no ill to him that has offended them: when any Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune befalls him, they triumph for joy at it: And when they ſay, I wiſh him no ill, but cannot endure to ſee him, nor have to do with him; this they call loving like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               <p>There is likewiſe I know not what ayre very repugnant to Charity, in the natural advantages of Wit, of Conduct, of Sence, of Ability; and in the excellency of other Qualities which, if one takes not great care, uſes to inſpire a love and eſteem of ones ſelf: For 'tis natural for him that has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more to undervalue him that has received leſs. But whilſt he thinks to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh himſelf from others by theſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, he corrupts his ſpirit, and in the end becomes utterly inſenſible of the moſt tender motions of Charity. For the reſt, as every one has ſhar'd in the diſtribution of natural or ſupernatural Gifts, according
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48587:59"/>to the meaſure of Grace; There is no Chriſtian but may take notice of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Gift his Brother has received from God, wherewith himſelf has not been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd. Thus S. <hi>Paul</hi> conſiders in S. <hi>Peter</hi> his Primacy, and again S. <hi>Peter</hi> conſiders in S. <hi>Paul</hi> the high Wiſdom he had received from Heaven. S. <hi>Anthony</hi> only regards in his Brethren thoſe Vertues himſelf had not, to honor them the more. 'Tis in this manner that the Chriſtian who has wit, eſteems one who has Vertue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Learned admires the Diſpatch of the Man of Buſineſs; The Man of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs praiſes the Capacity of the Learned. In fine, thus 'tis that Charity makes the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior not eſteem his own Dignity above others, but the Vertue and Merit of thoſe he Commands: And whilſt he exteriourly Commands them, he humbles himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriourly before them; and they on their ſide reſpect in him his Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and kindly ſubmit to his Conduct.</p>
               <p>Laſtly it may be ſaid, that the greateſt obſtacle to Charity, is the Immoderate love of Riches; for this love cauſes Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity of Conſcience, Hardneſs of Heart, Independence, Pride, Inſolence, Contempt of the Poor, and an entire corruption of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And as this reſtleſs care of preſerving
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48587:59"/>his Goods poiſons the Soul of the Rich, ſo Covetouſneſs is the moſt abominable of all Vices, and moſt oppoſite to Charity: For the eſſential Character of Avarice is a falſe Prudence of the Fleſh, all whoſe Deſigns and Thoughts bound themſelves in the Perſon poſſeſſed by it; ſo that his Heart is locked up to all Sentiments of pity for the Wants of the Poor. A Man darkens his ſpirit by the Vapors of ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal a Paſſion; he fixes his Heart to the Goods of the Earth, as to his ſoveraign Good: If others poſſeſs them, he unjuſtly ſeizes them; he covets them criminally, if he cannot get them, and violates what's moſt ſacred in Society to enrich himſelf maugre his Conſcience, againſt which he ſhuts his Ears.</p>
               <p>But it ought to be obſerved, that 'tis not ſo much the Riches inſpire this Spirit of Hardneſs and Injuſtice, as the fixing too great a love on them: For <hi>Job</hi> was Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable in his abundance; his Wealth was ſo far from being an obſtacle to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that it was a means for his better pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing it. He was, as himſelf ſays, <hi>The father of the poor, and protector of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; His door was always open to thoſe in neceſſity, and with the wooll of his ſheep he clad the naked; He was the ſupport of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:48587:60"/>the widow and fatherleſs, the traveller was welcom to his houſe; And he refuſed nothing to any in want that crav'd his help.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides this good uſe that ought to be made of Riches according to the example of <hi>Job,</hi> whoſe life may ſerve as a pattern to a Chriſtian, to diſpoſe his heart to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: He muſt likewiſe, to attain this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, have frequent communication with God by Prayer and Meditation. 'Tis chiefly from Prayer theſe lights take birth in our hearts, which are the moſt pure ſprings of Chriſtian Charity and love of our Neighbours. For the ſame ſighs that form in our Souls the Spirit of Prayer, form there alſo the Spirit of Charity. The inward voice of the heart; <hi>That Voice,</hi> ſays St. Auguſtine, <hi>which expreſſes it ſelf by the ſighings of Prayer, is that which enkindles in us the fervour of this Vertue:</hi> For <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity becomes cold when the Heart becomes ſilent,</hi> ſays this great Saint. Thus one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Charitable, without being Devout; becauſe Devotion is the moſt common nouriſhment of the love of God and our Neighbour. This love grows cold by the diſtraction of Buſineſs, and is even extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the diſquiets of a too buſie Life. In effect, the true ſource of Charity, as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48587:60"/>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> aſſures us, is renouncing the love of the World, and indifference for temporal Goods: for tranſitory Goods weaken the Heart, by the confidence they give it in ſo frail a ſupport as is that of Riches.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe there is nothing more capable to inflame Charity in the Soul of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, then a fervent and lively Faith, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated with a perfect Confidence in God: For the Fire of Charity kindles it ſelf at the Ardors of Faith, which makes a Chriſtian act like a Child of God, and love the Poor as his Brother. In fine, the ſure and infallible way to acquire this Vertue, is by little and little to accuſtom our ſelves to practiſe Works of it: For by viſiting the Priſoner, comforting the Afflicted, helping the Neceſſitous, inſtructing the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, which are Actions may be done daily, and even ought to be performed if one pretends to Chriſtianity; he becomes inſenſibly Charitable, and attains that heavenly Wiſdom which is the portion of the Humble: and which without Study or Reaſoning pours into the Heart that inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Unction of the Spirit of God, which teaches to love our Neighbour. But it is not ſufficient to teach a Chriſtian the Means to become Charitable: he muſt alſo, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48587:61"/>him to become ſo, be ſhew'd his obligation to it by the moſt preſſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Three very powerful Motives to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite a Chriſtian to acquire the Vertue of Charity.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Motive is, That without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charitable one cannot be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; for it is in Charity alone conſiſts the true Spirit of Chriſtianity. Nature teaches Man to live with Man, but Grace obliges to love him. <hi>This is,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Paul, the plenitude of the Law of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi> All the Morality of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and all the depth of the Wiſdom of the Goſpel points only at the practice of this Vertue, which alone is the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſtian Perfection. <hi>Without Charity,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>neither Faith, nor Hope, nor the gifts of Prophecy, nor the gifts of Tongues, nor Martyrdom, nor any other Vertue, can be conſiderable in the ſight of God.</hi> It is Charity perfects Man, rectifies his Reaſon, and ſanctifies all his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48587:61"/>Actions. This makes humble, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makes proud: becauſe it nouriſhes Humility, and choaks Pride. All Vertues become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and all good Works fruitleſs to him that is not Charitable. 'Tis Charity that warms the Faithful, that animates his Hopes, and that juſtifies a Sinner. One may enter into the Marriage-Chamber of the <hi>Lamb</hi> without Virginity, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Charity. The ordinary life of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the exerciſe of a faithful and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverant Charity, may ſometimes be as meritorious in the ſight of God, as the moſt heroick Conflicts of the Martyrs; becauſe every Action of Charity, by the nature of its Motive, is a ſecret Sacrifice of his Intereſt or of his Pleaſure, and even of his Honor: for one cannot in effect love his Neighbour like a Chriſtian, without depriving himſelf of ſomething either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodiouſly, or againſt his Inclination; And all the beſt we do is ordinarily good for nothing, but by the influence of this Vertue. It is only through Charity that the Works of Piety are Chriſtian: This enobles the meaneſt Actions; and the weakeſt Reaſonings become ſtrong, when a little ſuſtain'd by it: and 'tis not the greatneſs of the things done for God that renders them conſiderable, but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:48587:62"/>of the Charity wherewith they are done. In brief, this heavenly Vertue, which is the pureſt food of the Soul, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifies even natural Defects and the groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Imperfections; and covers that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Sins whereunto Man is ſubject through the weakneſs of his Condition, as the Apoſtle ſays. Let us then ſeek after no other Practice of Devotion, ſince this alone contains all other Practices, as St. <hi>John</hi> inſtructs us; let us not ſtrain our Wits, according to the Spirit of this Age, with vain Reaſonings, in queſt of new ways to arrive at Perfection: Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with this the Saviour of the World has marked out to us; let us ſet our heart on this Vertue he moſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to us; let us not ſtifle in our ſelves this divine fire whereof Faith kindles the firſt flames in our hearts. Let us love our Brethren ſincerely, ſince we live on the ſame Bread, and have all the ſame Hopes. If we cannot contribute our Goods towards ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring the Poor, at leaſt let us ſigh to God for him; and thereby in ſome manner comfort him what we can for the ſhame he undergoes to ſigh ſo often to Men, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring their aſſiſtance. In fine, let us not by our hard-heartedneſs diſhonor the holy Name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> a Name of ſweetneſs
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:48587:62"/>and bounty; and ſince without being Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable one cannot be a Chriſtian, let us be Charitable in effect, not to be only Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in <hi>idea.</hi> The reciprocal need Men have of one another, is the foundation of their Society, and the natural principle of their Union; And ſhall not Charity be a bond ſtrong enough to unite Chriſtians by the reciprocal obligations they have to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt each other? for the Rich ought to help the Poor before Men, as the Poor help the Rich before God; in that the miſery of the one, becomes the fountain of the others merit and happineſs.</p>
               <p>The Second Motive to acquire Charity, is the pain wherewith God ſo ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes him that is not provided with this Vertue. In effect, as it is to break the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance of the New Teſtament, and after a manner renounce the Goſpel, not to love ones Neighbour; there is nothing more terrible then theſe Puniſhments wherewith the holy Scriptures threatens them that have not this love. <hi>And is it not juſt,</hi> ſaith S. Chryſoſtom, <hi>that he who does no kindneſs, ſhould receive none?</hi> But how dreadful a Judgment does the Saviour of the World pronounce againſt thoſe Scribes whereof St. <hi>Mark</hi> ſpeaks, who devour with ſuch injuſtice and violence the Goods of Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows?
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:48587:63"/>What Maledictions againſt thoſe cruel and mercileſs Phariſees whereof St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſpeaks? Virginity, how pleaſing ſoever to God, through the luſtre of its purity, is a Vertue reproved in the Goſpel, when ſever'd from Charity. The fooliſh Virgins, far from being received at the Nuptials of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> were treated as impudent Women; becauſe they took no care to make that proviſion of this Oyl of the Goſpel, which is the figure of Charity. In vain they renounced Pleaſure, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chaſtity; all their Vertues avail them nothing to juſtifie them to the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, who ſpake to them theſe words full of contempt, <hi>I know you not.</hi> Oh! if true Virgins are treated ſo ſeverely by the Son of God: if the wiſdom of their Conduct, if the command over their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, if the purity of their Heart, if ſo many victories obtain'd over ſo frail fleſh and ſo weak a Sex; In fine, if even the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of their Vertue is fruitleſs to them: What will become of thoſe Virgins that lead ſuch licentious and ſcandalous lives? But with what ſharpneſs do's <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> condemn his own Diſciples, becauſe they advis'd him, through want of Charity, to make fire fall from Heaven upon the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> that would not receive him? <hi>You
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:48587:63"/>know not,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>of what ſpirit you are,</hi> and how far 'tis contrary to mine. Is not the puniſhment of the wicked rich man in the Goſpel a moſt dreadful Example? and the Treatment he receiv'd, is it not terrible? After all, what Crime had he committed? he had not been Charitable; <hi>The hardneſs of his heart,</hi> ſays St. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, <hi>was the cauſe of his loſs.</hi> But O my God, how ſevere and dreadful a Judge art thou! for this rich man had done wrong to none: he made uſe of the Riches thou hadſt beſtowed upon him, without doing any Violence or Injuſtice. 'Tis true, but the ſuperfluities of his Table, the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſneſs of his Houſe. his Oppulency, as innocent as it is, cry for Vengeance before God; becauſe he employ'd not his Goods to relieve the Neceſſities of the Poor. Look then to your ſelves you Great ones of the Earth; If proſperity be in your Houſes, if you live at eaſe, if all things ſucceed to your deſires, Tremble amidſt theſe temporal Bleſſings: All your good Fortune is only a mark of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, unleſs you are Charitable. Power, Riches, Honours, you are but impediments to Salvation, if you be not employ'd in aſſiſting the Poor, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting him that is in oppreſſion. For if
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48587:64"/>the Rich could love the Poor, he would be ſaved; and his Riches which are true evils, would become true goods. But can one hear without terror thoſe threatning words of the Goſpel, capable of themſelves alone to make tremble the Great ones that live in all abundance. <hi>Wo to you rich of the earth!</hi> And why? Becauſe God, who is juſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandons the Rich to their own Appetites, and ſtrikes them with an inward blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which makes them inſenſible of all the motions of Grace, and all the lights of Heaven. This falſe Tranquility, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Peace they enjoy, is ſometimes one of the moſt terrible torments wherewith God puniſhes their hard-heartedneſs; and 'tis an aſſured ſign he leaves them to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency. But how great will be the confuſion and aſtoniſhment of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, when he ſhall appear before the dreadful Tribunal of the laſt Judgment; to hear this terrible Sentence, which an offended God ſhall pronounce in the fury of his rage and indignation? <hi>Away from me you curſed into fire everlaſting: for I was hungry, and you gave me not to eat; I was thirſty, and you gave me not to drink; I was naked, and you cloathed me not.</hi> O cruel torments, for a Soul to ſee her ſelf eternally depriv'd of God, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:48587:64"/>to her own deſpair; becauſe being Chriſtian ſhe was not Charitable. It is not of Impudicity, Envy, Choler, Violence or Blaſphemy, God ſpeaks in his laſt Judgment to condemn theſe Crimes; he only ſpeaks of Inſenſibility towards the Poor; And <hi>Judgment without mercy to him that ſhews not mercy,</hi> as the Apoſtle aſſures us. It is thus thoſe mercileſs Souls ſhall be treated that have not been moved with the miſeries of their Brethren. But can any one bear in mind the thoughts of this dreadful Tribunal, and not be Charitable? And what hope can he have of the mercy of God, when himſelf has pity on none? 'Tis a ſign one has no Faith, when he is not ſeis'd with horror at ſuch terrible Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, and that would make one tremble when ſeriouſly conſider'd: for the Threats of a God are never in vain; and he is as dreadful in his Judgments, as he is amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his Mercies.</p>
               <p>If yet there be any found inſenſible of theſe Reaſons, becauſe their Effects are at a diſtance; let him at leaſt conſider after what manner God exerciſes his Judgments in this Life on ſuch Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as have not Charity: let him trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at reading in the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Menaces wherewith that dreadful
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:48587:65"/>Judge who carries a ſharp Sword in his Mouth, and holds Death fetter'd in Irons, ſtrikes thoſe firſt Paſtors of the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> becauſe their Charity, the Seal as it were of their Character and Spirit of their Vocation, was grown cold. Let him behold with trembling the terrible Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that unhappy <hi>Saprice</hi> mention'd by <hi>Metaphraſtus:</hi> who after the Rigors of a ſevere Priſon, after the Conflicts he had reſolutely ſuſtain'd before his Judge in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Faith, loſt his Crown at the very point of receiving it, and of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr became an Apoſtate and a Pagan; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not forgive his Brother an Injury. What ſhall I ſay of thoſe fearful pains wherewith God puniſhes in this Life; the ſhameful attaſh the Rich have to the Goods of the Earth; delivering them up a prey to their Appetites, and leaving them in an utter forgetfulneſs of their Salvation? <hi>For a rich Man,</hi> ſays S. Baſil, <hi>by locking up the bowels of Charity againſt his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, at the ſame time ſhuts thoſe of Gods Mercy againſt himſelf; and by treating ſo coldly</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the Perſon of the Poor, ſhews by his hard-heartedneſs that he fears not to have him for his Judge, whom he would not acknowledge for his Brother.</hi> It is a Heart perfectly hardned
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:48587:65"/>that, being no longer touch'd with any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of fear, rebells under the Rod, ſhuts his Ear againſt the checks of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and his Eyes againſt the light of his Reaſon; and becomes inſenſible of the motions of Humanity. 'Tis the moſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous pain wherewith God chaſtiſes the rich Man that dies in abundance, and leaves vaſt Wealth to his often unknown Heirs, without giving any ſhare to the Poor: He thinks not on't, becauſe God gives him not the Grace. He might obtain mercy by giving in Alms, at leaſt when he's dying, what Death will ſoon ſnatch from him: But this is a Reflection a rich Man is not worthy of; God abandons him to blindneſs and inſenſibility at his Death, in puniſhment of his hard-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs during his Life; to make him feel all the weight of his Juſtice, that regarded not his Mercy, which he ſlighted in ſlighting the Poor.</p>
               <p>'Tis from this inſolent contempt that there ariſe ſo many Diſorders in Families; hence comes the ruine of Houſes, the Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the publick Defamations, and all the ſhameful Faults of particular Perſons. The Providence of God permits to fall into theſe Misfortunes, thoſe who whilſt they made profeſſion of Chriſtianity, had not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:48587:66"/>any ſentiment of love or tenderneſs for their Neighbour; and were Chriſtians, but had not the Spirit or Character of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. But if the greatneſs of the Threats of the Son of God is able to frighten us, the greatneſs of his Recompences ought to have much more power over our Hearts to touch them.</p>
               <p>This is the Third Motive. In ſo ſhort a Treatiſe as I propos'd to my ſelf, it would be difficult to comprehend all the Rewards God has promi'sd to Charity; the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is full of them. 'Tis to this Vertue God has promis'd an unconcern for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Goods, firmneſs of Faith, purity of Manners, the comfort of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, tenderneſs of Devotion, unſhakable perſeverance in Vertue, and the infallible recompence of Salvation. God engages himſelf to pardon every thing in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Charity; for it is the ordinary propitiation of Sin. One Alms, one action of Clemency, the pardon of one Injury, one work of Mercy, is able to hide all the Faults that humane frailty can make us commit: Nothing purifies ſo much the Conſcience, nothing cleanſes more the Mind, then Alms-deeds. How many ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and humble Perſons have render'd themſelves worthy to penetrate the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:48587:66"/>of the holy Scriptures, and enter into the Secrets of God by the light of their Charity? It is a ſure protection againſt the frailty of Man, and againſt the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of offending God: ſince it reſiſts Sin, as the Scripture ſays. <hi>It is,</hi> ſaith St. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, <hi>the remedy againſt all Diſorders Man is ſubject to.</hi> This is of all other the moſt powerful Mediatour to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for it continually ſolicits this ſevere Judge, who is inflexible to all but Alms. This poor Man whom you have Clothed, this ſick Man you have Viſited, this innocent Creature to whom you have given your protection, and this afflicted Soul whom you have comforted, is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> For ſince <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> has told us that we do to him what we do to the leaſt of his Servants; <hi>There is no difference,</hi> ſays St. Chryſoſtom, <hi>between giving to the Poor, and giving to Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If then the Poor are Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to God, if their Interceſſion is the moſt aſſur'd aſſiſtance the Rich can expect from their Riches in that dreadful Day of the univerſal Judgment; place your hopes in this Treaſure of Gods Mercies, where neither Thieves nor Corruption can have acceſs. Nay be aſſur'd that 'tis your Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which will draw upon you the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Heaven in your temporal Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:48587:67"/>and in the afflicting Tribulations whereto the miſery of our Condition is ſo ſubject. For if you are Charitable, God will be faithful to the Promiſes he has made in his Prophet, <hi>You ſhall no ſooner open your mouth to call him to your aid, then he will anſwer, Here I am.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what blindneſs is it in a Chriſtian to have it in his power to merit Heaven by a Glaſs of Water, or a Morſel of Bread given to a poor Man out of the motive of Chriſtian Charity; and to refuſe it him? With what face can he beg pardon of God daily, if himſelf pardons not? Would you have others take pity on you? take pity on others. Do you crave Favours? do them your ſelf. Do not judge, if you will not be judged; for as you treat your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, your ſelf ſhall alſo be treated. After all, what Recompence can move a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Heart, if Heaven cannot, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in it ſelf alone all Rewards; and is only promis'd to the Charitable? For the Goſpel teaches us that the Saviour of the, World in that terrible Day wherein he ſhall Judge the Univerſe, will ſhew mercy only to thoſe that have been merciful: ſince in opening the Heavens to his Elect he will ſay to them theſe words, <hi>You who have clothed and fed me in the perſon of the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:48587:67"/>Poor, come receive an eternal reward which I have prepar'd for your mercies.</hi> Behold, what the price is of Chriſtian Charity: it merits an eternal recompence by a piece of Bread given to a poor Man for the love of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> it gains heavenly Goods by earthly ones, and for periſhable Riches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives thoſe will never periſh. Behold what Vertue the Spirit of Chriſtianity has in it to produce the ſolid fruits of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by mean, weak, and ſlight Works: For how many Chriſtians are there that ſanctifie a Life, in other reſpects but ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, nay ſometimes imperfect, by the ſole exerciſe of Charity? How many Souls have been rais'd to a ſublime perfection by the only practice of this Vertue, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in it ſelf all the perfection of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity?</p>
               <p>Theſe are Motives capable to make im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on a Heart that is prevented by the light of Faith, and is really touch'd with the hopes of what our Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to us. But ſince we are in an Age wherein Chriſtian Charity is much cool'd by the nicety of ſo many new Intereſts brought into the World, which divide Mens minds: let us endeavour to reinforce the heat of this Vertue by Conſiderations ſtill more preſſing, being its practice is ſo neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:48587:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Concluſion of this Diſcourſe by way of Exhortation, to move Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to Charity.</head>
               <p>IF the Spirit of Chriſtianity be nothing elſe but the Spirit of Charity, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this Diſcourſe; let us ſee if we are Charitable, to judge whether we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. For the Law of Charity is the Law of the New Teſtament written in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of our hearts, by the Impreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt: So that it would be ſtrange that Chriſtians inſtructed in a School of Unity, modell'd by the ſame Maxims, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with the ſame Blood, fed with the ſame Bread; that have the ſame Faith, the ſame Hope, and are one day to be reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame Glory, ſhould not have the ſame Spirit, and love one another. But after all how go's it? have we Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity one for another? The Luxury, Self-intereſt, Ambition, and general Irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Manners of this Age, have they not ſpread every where the Spirit of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? and what judgment ought one to make of the Chriſtianity of theſe later Times, wherein Animoſities, Jealouſies,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:48587:68"/>Law-Suits, Quarrels, Envies, Calumnies, Repinings, Injuſtices, and Revenge, reign with ſo much heat? Were there ever ſeen ſo many Diviſions in Families, ſo many Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in Marriages, ſuch Coldneſs and Indifferency among Relations, ſo little Union in Communities, and ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Opinions in Religion? Men have no Charity for thoſe they know, how then can they have any for them they know not? They love not their Kindred, how then can they love others? They are rigid to their Domeſticks, and can they have any tenderneſs for Strangers? Never did Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry more reign in the World, and perhaps the Poor were never leſs aſſiſted. Are we Chriſtians with ſuch languiſhing Manners? Thoſe later Times when Men ſhall hate one another, and the Charity of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grow ſo cold: Thoſe Times I ſay fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by our Lord, are they already come?</p>
               <p>However, let us tremble, if we have not Charity: For without it all our hopes are vain; and we are degenerated from the Spirit of the firſt Chriſtians, who gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly renouncing all the Goods of the Earth, only rais'd their Minds to Heaven, and made the purity of their Faith ſhine to the whole World by the ardor of their Charity. Let us then not ſtray out of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:48587:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſure way of Salvation which they have marked out to us by the exerciſe of this Vertue, they have practis'd with ſo much perſeverance and fidelity: Let us not ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle in our ſelves the ſentiments of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which our Chriſtianity gives birth to: Let us examine our ſelves, and ſee if we have that Seal of our Predeſtination ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly ſhew'd us in the Goſpel: Let us be afraid of loſing the features of this divine Character, for fear we loſe at the ſame time the marks and ſureſt pledge of our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Let us be touch'd with compaſſion for our Brethren, that God may be touch'd with compaſſion for us: Let us aſſiſt them in their wants, that God may aſſiſt us in ours: Let us be merciful to them, that he may be ſo to us: Let us not judge them, for our Judgments muſt one day be judged; or if we judge them, let it be without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them, that we be not condemned; for we ſhall be judged in the ſame manner we judge: Let us not hope God will ſtretch out to us his helping hand, if we refuſe help to the Afflicted that ask it. What pride would it be to behold with ungrateful Eyes <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> pouring forth his precious Blood upon the Croſs for us; and to deny him a bit of Bread which he begs of us by the mouth of the Poor: And what unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:48587:69"/>for us, ſhould theſe Riches that give us nothing but inquietude, and which we muſt one day quit, become an obſtacle to our Salvation; God having given them us only by their means to ſave us? How happy is he who, to make a good uſe of them, abandons the love of his Treaſures, to reſerve for himſelf none but thoſe of the Riches of Gods mercy at the day of his wrath.</p>
               <p>But the Juſtice of this dreadful Judge has Secrets and Abyſſes impenetrable to our underſtanding: His Grace is not for the Rich or Great ones of the Earth, who, through monſtrous hardneſs of heart, are become ſo inſenſible of the motions of pity, that they ſee the miſeries of the Afflicted without the leaſt compaſſion. Alaſs, if this poor wretch that carries ſorrow in his Face; this poor wretch that is your Brother; in fine, this poor wretch that repreſents <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in perſon cannot move you: what can? If you have been ſo cruel to ſhut up your bowels againſt his wants: how can you have the confidence of the truly faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who place all their hopes in the bowels of their Saviour; whence flow thoſe ſprings of mercy which are the ſanctuary of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? With what aſſurance will you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Sovereign Tribunal of the laſt Judgment, to render an account of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:48587:70"/>your Life to that inflexible Judge, who will give to every one according to his works; if you have been hard and pitileſs to all the world? But alaſs, how frightful will it be to hear thoſe terrible words of the Goſpel, <hi>Go you accurſed,</hi> and what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; after having neglected to clothe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> when he was naked, to feed him when he was hungry in thoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers whereof he is Head? He muſt be very blind, to think himſelf ſecure againſt the Sentence of ſo ſevere a Judge that ſees all things, when one has ſo contemn'd him in the perſon of his Brethren.</p>
               <p>But it is a dreadful heedleſneſs, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal blindneſs to which God uſes to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thoſe that permit themſelves to be hardned by covetouſneſs and pride of the Grandeurs of this World; and that are ſo cruel to treat their own Brethren more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidly then they do the very Beaſts they make uſe of for their Vanity. If God will one day call a Chriſtian to account for an idle word; what account will he demand of the idle Expences of the moſt part of the Great ones, and of all the Abuſes committed in the adminiſtration of the Eſtate he has given them? For the Eſtate which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows is no longer his to whom he gives it, when he has taken what is needful and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:48587:70"/>ſeemly for his Quality: It is the Poors when the Poor are in want. This is the reaſon why the Prophet calls Alms a piece of Juſtice, not Mercy: <hi>He diſtributed,</hi> ſays he, <hi>what he had to the poor, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his juſtice remaineth for ever.</hi> You poſſeſs not your Goods as ſoon as you are a Chriſtian, but to diſtribute them. Give little if you have but little; but give much if you have much. For what greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance can a Father leave his Children, then the Protection of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> whom he has ſuccoured in the Neceſſitous that had recourſe to his aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Happy he that comprehends this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery! it is a Secret unknown to earthly Souls, that dream not what advantage it is to regard the wants of the Neceſſitous out of the ſincere Motive of Chriſtian Charity. Happy he I ſay that underſtands it! He ſtarts not back at this ignominious out-ſide, nor at the miſerable condition of the Poor; becauſe he beholds <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> conceal'd under that mean Aſpect, and theſe Rags: He minds not the poorneſs of his Clothes; he conſiders the price of his Soul. That ulcerous Body in tatter'd Garments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to him not unworthy his aſſiſtance; for he is favourably look'd on by Heaven from the Minute he is truly poor: ſo he
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:48587:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>receives him as an Embaſſador ſent from God to treat of Peace with him, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate the Affair of his Salvation: He hopes the Alms he gives him will be the cauſe of his Predeſtination, and ſource of his Glory. Behold what a Chriſtian ought to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, when he ſees a poor Body: and once again, happy he that comprehends it. If we then are truly Chriſtians, as we glory to be; let us follow this admirable counſel S. <hi>Paul</hi> gave to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> to raiſe them up to the height of that Spirit he inſpir'd into them, conformable to the Image he had traced forth to them of the <hi>New Man</hi> he Preach'd to them: <hi>Put you on therefore as the elect of God,</hi> (that is, as Chriſtians) <hi>put you on,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the bowels of mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, modeſty, patience, ſupporting one one another, and pardoning one another, as alſo our Lord hath pardoned you.</hi> Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, wholly clad as he is with our frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, teaches us to pardon our Enemies, by his pardoning us who are his. We are ſo nice, we cannot bear with thoſe that do us the leaſt Offence; and yet we boaſt we are Diſciples of a God who pardons his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners, dies for thoſe that crucifi'd him, and who in ſpite of our Ingratitude, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to ſhowre down upon us his Favours, and the continual marks of his Bounty.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:48587:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>I do not bid you quit your Eſtates like the firſt Chriſtians, who went and laid them at the Apoſtles feet. I do not ſay to you, Go affront Tyrants, like the Martyrs, to make an eminent Profeſſion of your Faith. I ſay not, Retire your ſelf into the Wilderneſs, to lead a penitent Life like the <hi>Anchorites:</hi> Sell your Liberties, as St. <hi>Paulinus</hi> did; Or croſs the Seas like St. <hi>Xaverius;</hi> though God deſerves all this and more from you. I do not propoſe unto you the Lives of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as the moſt holy Model, and true Rule of Evangelical perfection. I only ſay to you, Do not tear in pieces your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Reputation; Pardon this Enemy, relieve this poor Man, this is ſufficient for you. I do not ſay to you, Save ſo many Souls that periſh; I only ſay, Save your ſelf: your Soul is your next Neighbour, loſe it not. Love thoſe you are to live with; but love them with a pure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Charity, which neither your own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts nor the Artifice of Men may ever alter: that the Unity of ſpirit which ought to be among the Faithful may not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced.</p>
               <p>Let us leave Spiritual Fathers to invent new Methods of Devotion, to ſatisfie the humour of the Age that pretends ſo much
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:48587:72"/>to Curioſity. Let us bluntly ſtop at the practice of this Vertue, without ſeeking after any perfecter way to go to God: ſince neither St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> nor the Goſpel it ſelf have ever own'd a better.</p>
               <p>In fine, let us be Charitable if we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Chriſtians, ſince Charity is the true Spirit of Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48587:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
